. >> GOOD AFTERNOON AND WELCOME
TO THE SEPTEMBER 1ST 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL. THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT
SUPERVISOR CHAN PRESENT CHAN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN
PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
PRESENT SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESENT MANDEL MANDOLIN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL PRESENT SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WONG WONG
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF
THE ROMITA COLONY WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE
INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAMAKRISHNA LONI HAVE NEVER
CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELAND. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE
RAMAKRISHNA COLONY COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
>> COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? >> I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE
FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA TO THE REPUBLIC FOR
WHICH STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE FOR ALL. >> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS
PARTICULARLY KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR ATTENDANCE IN PERSON HERE
IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER LOCATED WITHIN CITY
HALL IN ROOM 250 ON THE SECOND FLOOR AND WE ARE NOT ABLE TO BE
HERE. THE PROCEEDINGS ARE AIRING LIVE
ON AS OF JEHOVAH TV'S LOCAL CABLE CHANNEL OR LIVE STREAMING
AT S.F. JOVI TV DAWG. AND AS OF JULY 1ST PURSUANT TO
SB 707 THE FULL BOARD WILL TAKE REMOTE PUBLIC COMMENT DURING
THE PUBLIC COMMENT. WE WILL PRIORITIZE THOSE WHO
HAVE JOINED US HERE IN PERSON AND THEN HEAR FROM THOSE ON THE
REMOTE CALLERS SYSTEM. THE BOARD HAS ALSO APPROVED A
RULE TO ADDRESS DISORDERLY PUBLIC COMMENT.
MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC PLEASE KEEP YOUR COMMENTS GERMANE TO
THE MATTERS WITHIN THE SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION OF THE
BOARD. ANY COMMENTS THAT CONTAIN
PERSONAL ATTACKS HARASSMENT OR DISCRIMINATORY REMARKS DIRECTED
TO A CITY EMPLOYEE INCLUDING BOARD MEMBERS ARE OUTSIDE THE
SCOPE OF THIS BODY AND SHALL BE REDIRECTED AND FAILURE TO
IMMEDIATELY REDIRECT THOSE COMMENTS WILL RESULT IN THAT
INDIVIDUAL'S FORFEITURE OR OF THE REMAINING TIME AND WE WILL
TRANSITION TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
PLEASE REMEMBER TO ADDRESS YOUR COMMENTS TO THE BOARD AS A
WHOLE NOT TO INDIVIDUAL MEMBERS.
AND IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING
YOU CAN SEND AN EMAIL TO BOSS AT SAFEGUARD TALK OR USE THE
POSTAL SERVICE. >> JUST ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON BE GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244
SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102.
AND LASTLY, IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A REASONABLE
ACCOMMODATION FOR A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS
WITH DISABILITY ACT OR NEED TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE,
PLEASE CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE TWO BUSINESS DAYS
IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
>> THANK YOU MEMBERS MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR
MEETING MINUTES. APPROVAL OF THE JUNE 30TH 2026
JULY 7TH, 2026 AND JULY 14TH 2026 BOARD MEETING MINUTES.
>> COLLEAGUES, COULD I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES
AS PRESENTED MOVES BY CHAIR AND SECONDED BY CHERYL?
>> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED? SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN AND I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN MANDOLIN
EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE
APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEMS ONE THROUGH
22 TOGETHER ITEMS ONE THROUGH 22 ARE 22 ORDINANCES THAT AMEND
THE PLANNING CODE TO DESIGNATE THE FOLLOWING PROPERTIES AS
LANDMARKS AND MAKES THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
ITEM ONE DESIGNATES THE ALEXANDER ADAMS HOME LOCATED AT
1450 MASONIC AVENUE ITEM TO DESIGNATE IT'S THE BORING HOME
LOCATED AT 99 DAVIS ADERO STREET.
ITEM THREE DESIGNATES THE CHARLES CAT'S HOME LOCATED AT
1200 DELORA STREET. ITEM FOUR DESIGNATES THE
CHARLES L HINKLE HOME LOCATED AT 740 CASTRO STREET.
ITEM FIVE DESIGNATES THE DATE YOUR HOST HOME JAMES C HORMEL
MANSION LOCATED AT 181 ONE OF VISTA AVENUE EAST.
ITEM SIX LANDMARK DESIGNATION FOR THE DEBAUCHED TRIANGLE
CREEK REVIVAL HOME LOCATED AT 2173 15TH STREET.
ITEM SEVEN DESIGNATES THE EARLY HAIGHT ASHBURY FARMHOUSE
LOCATED AT 11 PIEDMONT STREET. ITEM EIGHT DESIGNATES THE
ELLIOT M WILSON HOME LOCATED AT 1335 GUERRERO STREET.
>> ITEM NINE DESIGNATES THE ENGINE COMPANY NUMBER 44 THE
ADAMS VAN HEUSEN HOUSE LOCATED AT 3816 22ND STREET.
ITEM TEN DESIGNATES THE GUERRERO STREET DOUBLE STICK
EAST LAKE HOME LOCATED AT 1415 AND THROUGH 1417 GUERRERO
STREET. ITEM 11 DESIGNATES THE HENRY
STREET ROWHOUSES LOCATED AT 191 THROUGH 197 HENRY STREET.
ITEM 12 DESIGNATES THE HOLY INNOCENTS CHURCH LOCATED AT 455
FAIR OAK STREET. ITEM 13 DESIGNATES THE JOHN C
JOHN J. CLARK HOUSE LOCATED AT 210
DOUGLAS STREET. ITEM 14 DESIGNATES THE MISSION
CONGREGATIONAL CHURCH LOCATED AT 3689 19TH STREET.
ITEM 15 DESIGNATES THE PHENIX BREWERY LOCATED AT 552 NO EAST
STREET. ITEM 16 DESIGNATES IS THE
RICHARD SPRECKELS MANSION ONE OF EAST A STUDIOS LOCATED AT
737 BUENA VISTA AVENUE WEST. ITEM 17 DESIGNATES THE SECOND
CHURCH OF CHRIST SCIENTIST LOCATED AT 651 DOLORES STREET.
ITEM 18 DESIGNATES THE A KEY HOUSE LOCATED AT 657 HENRY
STREET. ITEM 19 DESIGNATES THE WILLIAM
SHAUGHNESSY HOME LOCATED AT 394 FAIR OAK STREET.
ITEM 20 DESIGNATES THE FERNANDO NELSON HOME LOCATED AT 701
CASTRO STREET. ITEM 21 DESIGNATE THE LING
HOUSE LOCATED AT 199 CARL'S STREET.
AND ITEM 22 DESIGNATES THE ENGINE COMPANY NUMBER 33
LOCATED AT 117 BROAD STREET. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK,
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS ONE THROUGH 22.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
EYES SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
EYE AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I.
>> THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES ARE
FINALLY PASSED. >> PLEASE CALL ITEM 23 ITEM 23
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO ACCEPT AN IRREVOCABLE OFFER OF PUBLIC
INFRASTRUCTURE ASSOCIATED WITH THE HUNTER'S VIEW HOPE S.F.
PROJECT PHASE TWO TO DEDICATE SAID PUBLIC IMPROVEMENTS FOR
PUBLIC USE FOR PUBLIC STREET AND ROADWAY PURPOSES TO ACCEPT
FOR CITY MAINTENANCE AND LIABILITY PURPOSES TO
ESTABLISH THE OFFICIAL STREET GRADES, THE SIDEWALK WIDTHS
AND THE PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY WIDTHS TO ALSO AMEND ORDINANCE
NUMBER 1061 PERTAINING TO THE REGULATION OF THE WIDTH OF
SIDEWALKS TO ESTABLISH THE OFFICIAL SIDEWALK WIDTHS ON
CATALINA STREET, FAIRFAX AVENUE, INGLES STREET AND HIS
AVENUE IRONWOOD WAY AND MIDDLE POINT ROAD TO ACCEPT AN OFFER
OF DEDICATION FOR PHASE TWO EASEMENTS TO DELEGATE AUTHORITY
TO THE PUBLIC WORKS DIRECTOR TO ACCEPT THE PHASE THREE PUBLIC
INFRASTRUCTURE TO INCLUDE AUTHORITY TO TAKE ALL PHASE TWO
AND PHASE THREE ACTIONS TO AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF
PROPERTY TO EXECUTE DEEDS AND EASEMENT AGREEMENTS AS
SPECIFIED TO ACCEPT A PUBLIC WORKS ORDER TO RECOMMEND
VARIOUS ACTIONS IN REGARD TO THE PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE
IMPROVEMENTS AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS FINALLY PASSED AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL OUR NEW
BUSINESS. >> PLEASE CALL ITEM 24 ITEM 24
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO ALLOW
DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS TO SATISFY STREETS TREE PLANTING
REQUIREMENTS THROUGH PAYMENT OF AN IN LIEU FEE OR PROVIDING
ALTERNATIVE LANDSCAPING TO EXEMPT NECESSARY DWELLING UNITS
FROM STREET TREE PLANTING REQUIREMENTS TO ELIMINATE
APPEALS TO THE BOARD OF APPEALS FOR HAZARDOUS TREE REMOVALS
UNDERTAKEN BY CITY DEPARTMENTS AND COMMISSIONS TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO SPECIFY A SEPARATE ACCOUNT WITHIN THE
ADOPTED TREE FUND TO RECEIVE IN LIEU FEES FOR STREET TREE
REQUIREMENTS TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO UPDATE STREET
TREE APPLICABILITY REQUIREMENTS TO AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX
REGULATIONS CODE TO PRESCRIBE TIMEFRAMES FOR THE HEARING
AND DECISIONS ON APPEALS OF CERTAIN STREET TREE REMOVALS TO
THE BOARD OF APPEALS TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
DOES ANYONE NEED A ROLL CALL ON THIS?
>> OKAY, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL UP SUPERVISOR
SAUTER MAKE SURE THIS NEW SYSTEM IS WORKING.
>> THANK YOU FOR PRESIDENT. I WILL BE VOTING AGAINST THIS
ITEM TODAY AND I DO THINK IT HAS EVOLVED TO A BETTER PLACE.
I APPRECIATE THE COMMITTEE MEMBERS FOR THEIR AMENDMENTS TO
GET IT TO THIS POINT BUT ON THE WHOLE I THINK THIS HAS AN EQUAL
CHANCE OF MAYBE IMPROVING SOME THINGS AS IT DOES DETRACTING
FROM WHAT WE REALLY SHOULD BE FOCUSED ON HERE WHICH IS A
HEALTHIER TREE CANOPY AND STRONGER NEIGHBORHOODS.
YOU KNOW SPECIFICALLY I'M WORRIED ABOUT THE FACT THAT IF
WE DON'T PLANT THESE TREES AT THE TIME OF CONSTRUCTION
AND DEVELOPMENT THAT WE MAY NEVER GET THEM PLANTED AGAIN
AND I LIKE THAT THIS DOES POTENTIALLY OPEN UP SOME
FLEXIBILITY WITH WHERE WE'RE PLANTING TREES BECAUSE THAT'S
SOMETHING THAT WE ARE CONSTRAINED ON RIGHT NOW.
BUT ALL THINGS THAT I WOULD MUCH RATHER SEE US PUT OUR TIME
AND ENERGY TOWARDS THE THINGS THAT I HEAR ON A VERY, VERY
REGULAR BASIS FROM CONSTITUENTS FIRST AND FOREMOST THAT IS THE
MAINTENANCE AND PRUNING OF OUR EXISTING TREES.
EVERY FEW DAYS OUR OFFICE HEARS ABOUT A PARTICULAR TREE THAT A
NEIGHBOR IS WORRIED EXCUSE ME WORRIED ABOUT AND WE HAVE VERY
LITTLE RECOURSE. WE WERE YEARS LATE IN ACTUALLY
DOING OUR FIRST ROUND OF OF MAINTENANCE AND PRUNING OF OUR
EXISTING TREES. SO THERE'S WORK THAT NEEDS TO
BE DONE THERE AND THEN ULTIMATELY PUTTING OUR ENERGY
TOWARDS FINDING A MORE SUSTAINABLE SOURCE OF FUNDING
FOR NEW TREE PLANTING. SO THAT'S WHERE I'D RATHER SEE
US PUT OUR OUR ENERGY RATHER THAN THIS AND FOR THOSE REASONS
I'LL BE VOTING NO. SO THIS IS LAND IS CHAIR MUGAR
THANK YOU SO MUCH. THIS ITEM CAME OUT OF THE LAND
USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AND I WILL BE VOTING
TO SUPPORT IT AND I JUST WANTED TO ADDRESS A COUPLE OF THE
POINTS THAT I HAVE HEARD FROM MANY ADVOCATES WHO OPPOSE THIS
LEGISLATION AND TO EXPLAIN WHY I'M VOTING FOR IT.
FIRST OF ALL, I WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR WANG
FOR HIS WORK AND HIS STAFF'S WORK ON THIS.
>> I DO THINK THAT IT MAKES IT EASIER FOR SMALLER PROPERTY
OWNERS, MOSTLY HOMEOWNERS ON THE WEST SIDE TO ADD THOSE
AVENUES TO DENSIFY THEIR PROPERTIES WHICH IS WHAT WE
WANT. >> BUT I ALSO SORT OF REALLY
WANT TO REJECT SOME OF THE TALKING POINTS ABOUT HOW THIS
WILL NEGATIVELY AFFECT THE TREE CANOPY.
I THINK THE UNDERPINNING OF THAT ARGUMENT IS THE MISTRUST
OF GOVERNMENT THAT SOMEHOW GOVERNMENT WILL NOT DO THE WORK
AS EFFECTIVELY AS A PRIVATE SECTOR AND THAT COLLEAGUES IS A
CONSERVATIVE REPUBLICAN TALKING POINT AND I HAVE NONE OF IT.
I WILL HAVE NONE OF IT THESE WORKERS ARE REPRESENTED BY
LABORERS UNION TO 61. THEY'RE OUT THERE DOING THE
WORK EVERY DAY. THEY ACTUALLY DO A REALLY GOOD
JOB IN ADDRESSING THE RACIAL DISPARITY AND TREE CANOPY
BETWEEN WEALTHIER NEIGHBORHOODS AND LOW INCOME NEIGHBORHOODS
AND I THINK ARE WE PERFECT? NO.
ARE WE DONE? NO.
BUT I THINK THAT HAVING THE PLAN AND CENTRALIZING IT
AND HAVING IT BE A GOAL OF OUR DEPARTMENT IS A REALLY GOOD
THING. THE SECOND THING THAT I WANT TO
ADDRESS IS THE NUMBERS THAT HAVE BEEN THROWN OUT IN THE
PRESS. IT'S BEEN REPORTED THAT IT COST
BETWEEN 4000 AND $6000 PER TREE TO PLANT IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I DON'T KNOW WHERE THOSE NUMBERS COME FROM AS WE ALL
KNOW HERE BY LAW GOVERNMENT CANNOT CHARGE MORE THAN IT
COSTS TO PERFORM THE FUNCTION AND IT COST SAN FRANCISCO ABOUT
$2,600 PER TREE AND MOST OF THAT COSTS ABOUT $2,000.
OF THAT $2,600 COST IS WATER FOR THREE YEARS BECAUSE WE TAKE
IT UPON OURSELVES TO PUT IT ON A SCHEDULE TO WATER THOSE TREES
SO THAT THEY SURVIVE AND FRANKLY THE GOVERNMENT THE
LOCAL GOVERNMENT DOES A LOT BETTER JOB THAN THE PRIVATE
DEVELOPERS WHO THEN SELL AND CHANGE OWNERSHIP OF
DEVELOPMENTS THAT THEN GO TO SOMEONE ELSE.
SO WHILE WE STILL ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR COMPLIANCE OF
THAT, I THINK GOVERNMENT DOES A MUCH BETTER JOB IN DOING THAT
THAN THE PRIVATE SECTOR. SO FOR THOSE REASONS I DO THINK
THAT THIS IS A GOOD STEP. I THINK IT WILL HELP US YOU
KNOW, PLAN BE STRATEGIC ABOUT WHERE WE'RE PLANTING
AND KEEPING THOSE TREES ALIVE AND I WILL BE SUPPORTING THIS
LEGISLATION. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THE PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN,
COLLEAGUES, THERE ARE FEW REASONS WHY I'M VOTING NO ON
THIS LEGISLATION. FIRST, THIS LEGISLATION MAKES
IT MORE DIFFICULT TO PROTECT EXISTING TREE CANOPY BY
REMOVING THE APPEALS PROCESS FOR CITY TREES SLATED FOR
REMOVALS IN 2018. GUYMON THE QUATTRO IS SLATED TO
HAVE UP TO 78 TREES REMOVED AND THE RIGHT TO APPEAL LED TO
A NEGOTIATION AND CONSTRUCTIVE SETTLEMENT THAT SAVED
APPROXIMATELY 45 MATURE TREES ON THE LATINO CULTURAL
DISTRICTS MAIN CORRIDOR AND ADDED 100 MORE THROUGHOUT
THE CULTURAL DISTRICT. >> THIS WILL BE MORE DIFFICULT
IN THE FUTURE WITH THE REMOVAL OF THE APPEALS PROCESS.
>> SECOND, BY ALLOWING DEVELOPERS IN LIEU OF PAYMENT
FOR MANDATED TREE ALLOCATIONS, THIS LEGISLATION MAY
INADVERTENTLY PUT AT RISK NEIGHBORHOODS THAT ARE
UNDERREPRESENTED IN CANOPY AND GREEN SPACES.
>> AND FINALLY, I APPRECIATE THE ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE LENS
THAT MY COLLEAGUES HAVE INCLUDED AN IMPORTANT STEP TO
RECOGNIZING THAT LOW INCOME COMMUNITIES HAVE HIGHER
ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH BURDENS AND LOWER TREE CANOPIES THAT
CAN HELP COUNTER THESE FACTORS. HOWEVER, DEPENDING ON THE
ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE DETERMINATION MEASURES USE,
NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE THE MISSION MIGHT END OF BEING
DEPRIORITIZED. FOR THESE REASONS I'LL BE
VOTING NO ON THIS MEASURE. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMUD.
>> COLLEAGUES, I WANT TO THANK THE SPONSORS FOR BRINGING THIS
LEGISLATION FORWARD AND IN PARTICULAR THE NEW FEE OPTION
FOR SMALLER PROJECTS. I BELIEVE IS A GREAT STEP TO
MAKE BUILDING THE TYPES OF PROJECTS ENVISIONED BY THE
FAMILIES OWNING PLAN A LITTLE BIT EASIER WHILE ALSO
GENERATING MORE FUNDS FOR TREE PLANTING AND WATERING CITYWIDE.
I DO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT I ALSO DID HAVE MISGIVINGS ABOUT
THE LEGISLATION COMING DIRECTLY FROM EXPERIENCE IN DISTRICT
FIVE PARTICULARLY AROUND THE APPEALS PROCESS.
>> EARLIER THIS YEAR RESIDENTS IN THE LOWER HAIGHT AND THE
POST TRIANGLE LEARNED ABOUT SEVEN MATURE FICUS TREES ON
WALLER STREET THAT HAD BEEN SLATED FOR AN EMERGENCY REMOVAL
AS PUBLIC SAFETY HAZARDS. HUNDREDS OF RESIDENTS IN OUR
DISTRICT CONTACTED OUR OFFICE AND MORE THAN 800 PEOPLE SIGNED
A PETITION CONDEMNING THE REMOVAL.
>> MY OFFICE WORKED WITH PUBLIC WORKS TO SECURE A SECONDARY
REVIEW BY THE ACTING URBAN FORESTER WHICH RESULTED
ACTUALLY IN FOUR OF THE SEVEN TREES BEING PRESERVED.
THE REMAINING THREE STILL MOVE FORWARD WITH REMOVE REMOVAL AS
DETERMINED TO BE NECESSARY. >> THAT'S WHY IN COMMITTEE I
INTRODUCED AN AMENDMENT TO ALLOW FOR HAZARD TREE REMOVALS
TO STILL BE APPEALED TO THE DIRECTOR OF PUBLIC WORKS
AND THIS AMENDMENT WAS PASSED UNANIMOUSLY.
WE WANT PUBLIC WORKS TO GET THINGS RIGHT THE FIRST TIME BUT
IN THIS SITUATION A SECOND LOOK BY A QUALIFIED FORESTER
PROMPTED BY THE PUBLIC CHANGED THE OUTCOME FOR FOR MATURE
TREES AND DIDN'T HOLD UP THE THREE NEEDED TO COME DOWN.
NOW ANY TREES SUBJECT TO HAZARD TREE REMOVAL CAN STILL GET THAT
SECOND BLOCK HAZARD REMOVAL STILL MOVE QUICKLY AND NO
APPEAL TO THE BOARD OF APPEALS. NO REHEARING, NO DELAY
IN TAKING DOWN A TREE THAT POSES A RISK TO REAL DANGER TO
THE PUBLIC AND OUR WORKERS. >> WHAT IT PRESERVES IS A
CHANCE TO CATCH AN ERROR BEFORE A MATURE TREE COMES DOWN.
SO I WANT TO THANK PUBLIC WORKS IN THE MAYOR'S OFFICE FOR
WORKING COLLABORATIVELY WITH SAM LOGAN AND MY TEAM FOR
IMPROVING THIS LEGISLATION AND BASED ON THIS AMENDMENT I'M
COMFORTABLE MOVING FORWARD ON THIS ITEM AND WE'LL BE VOTING
IN SUPPORT. I WOULD LIKE TO INVITE A
REPRESENTATIVE OF PUBLIC WORKS TO MAYBE COME FORWARD
AND ANSWER A QUESTION OR TWO JUST HAD A GOOD CONVERSATION
WITH THE DIRECTOR SHORT EARLIER TODAY AND SORT OF THE PURPOSE
OF THIS IS TO KIND OF GET SOME OF THIS STUFF JUST ON THE
RECORD HERE. I'M A FORMER MEMBER OF THE
BOARD OF APPEALS. >> IT IS IT HURTS ME TO TAKE
JURISDICTION AWAY FROM THE BOARD OF APPEALS BUT FROM MY
CONVERSATION WITH DIRECTOR SHORT, IT SOUNDS LIKE THE WAY
IN WHICH THESE APPEALS AND THE NUMBER OF THESE APPEALS TO THE
BOARD OF APPEALS HAS INCREASED SIGNIFICANTLY WITH THE
PUBLICATION ONLINE OF INFORMATION ABOUT PROPOSED TREE
REMOVALS. >> AND I'M WONDERING IF YOU
COULD TALK A LITTLE BIT ABOUT WHAT IT HAS MEANT IN THE PAST
TO HAVE DELAYS AROUND SOME OF THESE REMOVALS WHERE IT'S LED
TO FAILURE, WHERE FAILURES HAVE HAVE HAPPENED PENDING THE
HEARING? >> AND TALK A LITTLE BIT ABOUT
THE ADMINISTRATIVE BURDEN OF THESE OF THESE HEARINGS.
>> BUT IT IS THE CONTENTION OF YOUR DIRECTOR AND YOUR
DEPARTMENT THAT IT HAS GROWN OVER TIME AND THAT IT IS, YOU
KNOW, AN IMPEDIMENT TO DOING SOME OF THE OTHER THINGS AROUND
TREES THAT SUPERVISOR SAUTER SUGGESTED MAYBE WE OUGHT TO BE
DOING. >> YES.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR. FOR THE RECORD MY NAME IS DAVID
MOORE AND THE SUPERINTENDENT OF THE BUREAU OF URBAN FORESTRY.
>> 20 YEARS AGO I EARNED A BACHELOR'S OF SCIENCE
IN FORESTRY. I'VE BEEN A CERTIFIED ARBORIST
FOR PROBABLY 18 YEARS AND LIKE MANY OF MY COLLEAGUES WHO ARE
ALSO CERTIFIED ARBORIST, I'M ALSO CERTIFIED IN TREE RISK
ASSESSMENT WHICH IS A VERY SPECIFIC TYPE OF TRAINING FOR
MANAGING THE RISK OF URBAN TREES.
>> AND I'D LIKE TO START BY PROVIDING A BACKGROUND OF WHAT
THAT METHOD IS JUST FOR CONTEXT PURPOSES.
TREE RISK IS MEASURED BY WHAT ARE THE CHANCES OF SOMETHING
BAD HAPPENING BASED OFF OF A DEFECT OF A TREE.
>> TIMES WHAT ARE THE CHANCES OF SOMETHING BEING UNDERNEATH
IT WHEN THAT HAPPENS TIMES WHAT'S THE MAGNITUDE OF THAT
CONSEQUENCE? AND A TREE IN THE FOREST EVEN
IF IT'S TOTALLY DEAD AND ABOUT TO FALL OVER IF THERE'S NOTHING
AROUND IT EXCEPT FOR FOREST IT ACTUALLY POSES ALMOST VIRTUALLY
NO RISK. SO WE HAVE TO CALCULATE IS
THERE PEDESTRIANS UNDERNEATH IT?
IS THERE FIXED ASSETS PROPERTY ?
IS THERE TRAFFIC UNDERNEATH? ARE THERE OTHER FACILITIES
INFRASTRUCTURE THAT COULD BE IMPACTED BY A TREE RISK WHICH
MAKES OUR JOB VERY DIFFICULT BECAUSE TREES NATURALLY CLOSE
THE LOOP WHEN THEY FALL DOWN IN A FOREST THEY WOULD JUST
UPCYCLE THE NUTRIENTS AND BECOME MORE FOREST.
BUT IN A CITY YOU CAN'T PEOPLE DON'T HAVE A VERY MUCH SMALLER
TOLERANCE FOR THAT TYPE OF IMPACT ESPECIALLY IF IT AFFECTS
THEM PERSONALLY. SO A CITY OF 125,000 STREET
TREES NEED TO BE MANAGED FOR RISK PURPOSES AND WE DO THIS
WITH A VERY SMALL NUMBER OF INSPECTORS THAT ARE TASKED WITH
TAKING IN SERVICE REQUESTS AS WELL AS ROUTINELY
AND INSPECTING THE TREES A TREE HAZARD MAY BE IDENTIFIED IN A
TREE AND THE FIRST STEP IS CAN IT BE MITIGATED?
THAT COULD BE DONE THROUGH PRUNING, FOR REMOVING DEADWOOD,
FOR PRUNING BACK BRANCHES, SHAPING THE TREE FOR STRUCTURE
AND OR MOVING THE ASSETS THAT IT COULD STRIKE UNDERNEATH
AND SAY IT HAS A LEAN IN ONE DIRECTION MAYBE MORE FOR
PRIVATE PROPERTY BECAUSE THEY OKAY WELL I'M GOING TO REMOVE
THE THINGS THAT ARE IN THAT DIRECTION AND YOU'VE MANAGED
THE RISK. PRESERVATION IS THE NUMBER ONE
GOAL AND TREE RISK MANAGEMENT AND YOU TAKE AS MANY MEASURES
AS YOU CAN TO LIMIT THE CHANCES OF THE TREE DAMAGING SOMETHING
AS A VERY LAST RESORT. WHAT A TREE BE SLATED FOR
REMOVAL AND THAT MEANS THAT THEY'RE THERE.
WE'VE EXHAUSTED REASONABLE MANAGEMENT TECHNIQUES THAT
COULD ABATE THE RISK WHETHER THE ASSETS UNDERNEATH IT CAN'T
BE RELOCATED, THE SITE CONDITIONS CAN'T BE CHANGED
AND THERE'S NO MANAGEMENT TECHNIQUE THAT WOULD FULLY SAVE
THE AREA FROM BEING AT RISK OF A TREE FALLING ON IT
AND HURTING SOMETHING OR KILLING SOMEBODY.
SO WE CAN'T BELIEVE THAT IN THE GRAND SCHEME OF 125,000 TREES
SO IT'S RARE THAT A TREE REALLY DOES COME DOWN AND IMPACT
SOMETHING BUT IF IT WERE TO IMPACT A PERSON OR THEIR
PROPERTY IT'S HIGHLY CONSEQUENTIAL TO THAT PERSON A
PROPERTY AND IT CAN LEAD TO INJURY FATALITY OR COSTS TO
PROPERTY DAMAGE AS WELL AS LEGAL CONSEQUENCES WHICH ARE
ALL SHOULDERED BY THE TAXPAYERS.
SO IT'S OUR RESPONSIBILITY TO USE OUR METHODOLOGY, OUR
TRAININGS, INDUSTRY STANDARDS AND BEST MANAGEMENT PRACTICES
TO LIMIT THOSE RISKS AND MANAGE THE URBAN FOREST.
AND THEN WHEN A TREE NEEDS TO BE REMOVED, THE GOAL IS TO
REPLACE IT WITH ANOTHER TREE THAT WILL BEGIN ITS LIFESPAN AS
UNFORTUNATELY ALL THESE TREES DO HAVE A FINITE LIFESPAN
AND IT'S OUR JOB TO TRY TO KEEP THEM IN THE SWEET SPOT OF BEING
GOOD NEIGHBORS TO THE REST OF US.
>> SO I WANTED TO PROVIDE THAT AS CONTEXT AND SUBJECT MATTER
EXPERTISE SUPERVISOR AND I'LL CONTINUE WITH YOUR QUESTION.
IT'S NOT COMMON THAT WE POST A TREE FOR A HAZARDOUS TREE FOR
REMOVAL AND IT GETS APPEALED. THE EXACT NUMBER IS DOCUMENTED
I BELIEVE IN THE FILES BUT OFF THE TOP OF MY HEAD IT'S A
HANDFUL OF TIMES OVER THE PAST FEW YEARS.
HOWEVER, THERE HAVE BEEN ENOUGH CASES IN RECENT YEARS WHERE A
HAZARDOUS TREE WENT THROUGH THE APPEALS PROCESS WHICH WE FULLY
RESPECT THE BOARD OF APPEALS AND THE FUNCTION THEY SERVE.
BUT IN THE FACE OF A HAZARDOUS TREE WHICH WE CAN USE OUR
METHODS TO MAKE OUR BEST ESTIMATES AND CALCULATION OF
THE RISK FACTOR THAT THERE'S GOING TO BE X FACTORS THAT ARE
TOTALLY OUT OF OUR CONTROL THE FORCES OF NATURE YOU KNOW A BIG
GUST OF WIND, SOMETHING INSIDE THE TREE IS BIOLOGICAL THAT
COULDN'T BE DETECTED AND IF DESPITE OUR EXPERTISE THAT TREE
CAN STILL FAIL, YOU KNOW, SUDDENLY WITHOUT ANY WARNING
AND WHEN IT DOES IF THERE'S A HIGH CONSEQUENCE TO WHAT'S
UNDERNEATH IT AND A HIGH CONSEQUENCE OF THE IMPACT, IT
COULD CAUSE SEVERE DAMAGE AND THERE'S BEEN A FEW CASES OF
THAT IN RECENT YEARS WHICH HAS MADE US CRINGE AND THINKING OMG
THIS IS IT'S OUR RESPONSIBILITY TO MANAGE THESE HAZARDS
AND IT'S HAPPENED ENOUGH TIMES THAT THE ADMINISTRATIVE PROCESS
GOES AT ITS OWN PACE AND THAT HAS LED TO US NOT BEING ABLE TO
REMOVE HAZARDOUS TREES WHILE THEY WERE MARKED FOR REMOVAL
WHILE THE WHILE THE APPEALS PROCESS WAS GOING ON.
I'M SYMPATHETIC TO THAT. I THINK ONE OF THE THINGS
THAT'S A LITTLE TROUBLING OR VERY TROUBLING IS THAT IN THE
LAST TEN YEARS AS THE CITIES ASSUMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR
STREET TREE MAINTENANCE, WE'VE SEEN MORE MORE OF THEM COMING
OUT THAN GOING IN. AND I SPOKE WITH DIRECTOR SHORT
ABOUT THAT AS WELL. SHE BELIEVES THAT THAT ERA IS
COMING TO AN END. >> THAT YOU HAVE THE REASON
THAT YOU'VE DONE THE WORK OF GETTING RID OF MANY OF THE
TREES THAT NEEDED TO BE TAKEN OUT AND THAT YOU HAVE THE
RESOURCES THAT ARE GOING TO HAVE THE RESOURCES TO BE ADDING
AT A FASTER CLIP THAN YOU ARE REMOVING.
>> BUT CAN YOU TALK A LITTLE BIT ABOUT WHY YOU AND SHE
BELIEVE THAT? THANK YOU FOR ANSWERING ASKING
THAT QUESTION. I'D BE GLAD TO ANSWER THAT.
WITH 125,000 STREET TREES THAT HAVE NEVER BEEN MANAGED AS A
POPULATION BEFORE OR SOME OF THEM AT ALL, THERE'S A LOT OF
BACKLOG OF THE YOU KNOW, IN A FOREST THE TREES DON'T NEED TO
BE PRUNED. THEY ALL GROW UP BECAUSE
THERE'S TREES ON EVERY SIDE SO THEY GROW TOWARDS THE SUN.
THEY DON'T HAVE BRANCHES THAT GO LIKE THIS IN A CITY.
THEY'RE SINGLE TREES AND THEY GROW LIKE THIS.
SO THEY NEED TO BE HEADED BACK. THEY COULD HAVE CROSSING LIMBS
. THEY COULD HAVE BRANCHES
GROWING INTO A BUILDING OR INTO A MUNI LINE AND ALL THESE
THINGS THAT ARE VERY COMPLICATED WITH ALL OF OUR
VERY COMPLICATED INFRASTRUCTURE AROUND THEM.
THE FIRST PASS AROUND ALL THE TREES IS GOING TO IDENTIFY A
LOT OF TREES WITH IRREPARABLE DEFECTS BECAUSE THEY HADN'T
BEEN MAINTAINED. WE HAVEN'T DONE ANY MITIGATING
MEASURES FOR SO MANY YEARS. >> THEY MAY HAVE BEEN ADDED TO
A LIST OF TREE REMOVALS THEN JUST THE AMOUNT OF WORK THAT
HAS TO GO THROUGH THE FIRST PASS OF TREE PRUNING SLOWS DOWN
THE PROCESS. BY THE END OF THIS CALENDAR
YEAR WE EXPECT TO COMPLETE THE FIRST ROUND OF STREET TREE
PRUNING THROUGH STREET TREE SRF WHICH WE'RE VERY PROUD OF.
I ALSO WANT TO SAY THAT WE'VE ADDED AS ASSISTANT
SUPERINTENDENT CHARLIE MURPHY WHO IS AT THE HELM OF THE
INSPECTION UNIT AND THE ARBORIST UNIT.
WE'RE SCALING UP WITH OUR CONTRACTS.
WE'RE WORKING WITH OUR COLLEAGUES IN PUBLIC WORKS TO
TO GET AN INCREASE THE CAPACITY FOR IMPLEMENTING CONTRACTS
AND PROP EADS FUNDS. THIS PROGRAM WE DO HAVE SOME
VACANCIES AND SOME OF THOSE THINGS ARE OUTSIDE OUR CONTROL
BUT WE'RE MAKING WINS DESPITE OUR VACANCIES AND INCREASING
OUR CAPACITY. WE'RE ALSO GROUPING OUR TREE
PRUNING IN A MORE LOGISTICALLY STREAMLINED WAY WHICH IS GOING
TO BUILD IN OPERATIONAL EFFICIENCIES AND WE HOPE TO
MAKE THE NEXT PASS OF STREET TREE PRUNING CLOSER TO OUR FIVE
YEAR RANGE. AND WE ARE PRETTY CONFIDENT
ABOUT ALL THE WORK THAT'S GOING INTO IT WILL LEAD TO THAT
RESULT AND YOU HAVE ADDITIONAL RESOURCES FOR NEW PLANTING THAT
YOU HAVE NOT HAD OVER THE LAST FEW YEARS FOR PLANTING.
WE HAVE BEEN WE HAVE SOUGHT OUT STATE AND FEDERAL FUNDS FOR
GRANTS. WE HAVE A $12 MILLION
INFLATIONARY REDUCTION AT GRANT FOR OUR TREE PLANTING.
WE JUST QUALIFIED AN RFP TO THROW A COMPETITIVE PROCESS TO
A SERVICE PROVIDER WHO IS STARTING TO PLAN A COUPLE
THOUSAND OF THOSE TREES. THERE'S GOING TO BE 3500 TREES
TOTAL PUBLIC WORKS ALREADY PLANTED 500.
SO WE ARE AGGRESSIVELY SEEKING ADDITIONAL OUTSIDE RESOURCES TO
INCREASE OUR TREE PLANTING GOALS TO GET CLOSER TO THE
GOALS THAT ARE SET BY THE CLIMATE ACTION PLAN.
AND IN FACT WE HAVE A NEW WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT GRANT
THAT HAS THAT IT'S IN THE PROCESS OF BEING SIGNED TODAY
THAT IS GOING TO BE FOCUSED ON FILLING 2000 VACANT TREE
PLANTING SITES. I KNOW THAT THERE HAS BEEN A
BIG DEMAND FOR THIS BACKLOG OF VACANT TREE PLANTING SITES TO
BE FILLED. IT'S REALLY HARD TO DO IT ONE
AT A TIME. SO WE PUT IN A LOT OF WORK
AND PLANNING TO THOUGHTFULLY WORK WITH ECONOMIES OF SCALE TO
PLANT 2000 OVER THE NEXT TWO YEARS.
>> AND WE HOPE THAT THIS WILL BE THE FIRST PHASE AND THAT WE
CAN CONTINUE AT THIS PACE IN FUTURE YEARS.
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU FOR ANSWERING SOME
QUESTIONS TONIGHT AND YOU MAY SIT DOWN.
ALL RIGHT. >> THANKS.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL IN THIS ITEM ON ITEM 24
SUPERVISOR ONE WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN.
NO SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN. EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER. FIELDER.
NO. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER NO SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO THERE ARE SEVEN EYES
AND FOUR NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS CHEN FIELDER, SAUTER AND WALTON
VOTING NO AND THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM
CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER RECOGNITION OF
COMMENDATIONS. >> YES IT'S NOW TIME TO
RECOGNIZE MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO DISTRICT FOR SUPERVISOR WONG.
MAY I HAVE THAT VOTES COME UP? >> OKAY.
COLLEAGUES, TODAY I'M HONORED TO RECOGNIZE BOTH FOR THEIR
EXTRAORDINARY WORK SUPPORTING OUR VETERANS AND AS WE MARK
SUICIDE PREVENTION MONTH WE ALSO RECOGNIZE THE VITAL ROLE
THAT COMMUNITY CONNECTION AND A RENEWED SENSE OF PURPOSE CAN
PLAY IN VETERANS LIVES. VET BOATS IS A VETERAN LED
ORGANIZATION THAT BRINGS VETERANS TOGETHER FOR
THERAPEUTIC SAILING, HANDS ON BOAT RESTORATION, MARITIME
SKILLS AND COMMENTARY. THE PROGRAMS GIVE VETERANS AN
OPPORTUNITY NOT ONLY TO LEARN AND WORK TOGETHER BUT ALSO TO
REBUILD CONFIDENCE, DEVELOP MEANINGFUL RELATIONSHIPS
AND REDISCOVER A SENSE OF PURPOSE FOR VETERANS LIVING
WITH PTSD AND OTHER CHALLENGES ASSOCIATED WITH THEIR SERVICE.
THAT SENSE OF CONNECTION CAN BE INCREDIBLY IMPORTANT.
WE KNOW THAT SUICIDE PREVENTION IS ABOUT MORE THAN INTERVENTION
AT A MOMENT OF CRISIS. IT IS ALSO ABOUT MAKING SURE
PEOPLE HAVE STRONG COMMUNITIES AROUND THEM PLACES WHERE THEY
FEEL VALUED, UNDERSTOOD, NEEDED AND SUPPORTED.
THAT IS WHAT MAKES THE WORK OF THAT BOAT SO MEANINGFUL.
THERE IS SOMETHING UNIQUELY POWERFUL ABOUT VETERANS
SUPPORTING OTHER VETERANS THROUGH DATA SHARED EXPERIENCE
WHETHER SAILING ON THE BAY, WORKING TOGETHER TO RESTORE A
BOAT OR SIMPLY SPENDING TIME WITH PEOPLE WHO UNDERSTAND
THEY'RE CREATING THE KINDS OF LASTING BONDS THAT CAN HELP
COMBAT ISOLATION AND STRENGTHEN RESILIENCE AND THE IMPACT
EXTENDS BEYOND INDIVIDUAL VETERANS WHEN WE SUPPORT THE
WELL-BEING OF THOSE WHO HAVE SERVED, WE ALSO SUPPORT THEIR
FAMILIES AND STRENGTHEN OUR BROADER COMMUNITY.
SO TODAY I WANT TO THANK EVERYONE AT VETS BOATS FOR YOUR
SERVICE, COMPASSION AND DEDICATION AND COMMEND YOU
FOR HELPING VETERANS THROUGHOUT THE BAY AREA FIND CONNECTION
PURPOSE, RESILIENCE AND HOPE. >> AND NOW IT'S MY PLEASURE TO
WELCOME MATT. MAY I HAVE A GENTLEMAN
GENTLEMAN FROM VET BOATS VETS BOATS TO SAY A FEW WORDS WELL
THANK YOU TO THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND TO THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS FOR ALLOWING ME TO COME UP.
JUST A QUICK INTRODUCTION. MY NAME IS MATT GETTLEMAN.
>> I LIVE IN DISTRICT FOUR AT SEACLIFF.
I WORK AT GOLDMAN SACHS DOWNTOWN AND I'M ALSO A
VETERAN. SO I WENT TO WEST POINT, SERVED
FIVE YEARS IN THE ARMY SO THANK YOU AGAIN FOR HAVING US.
SO WHAT I'D LIKE TO SAY ABOUT THE ORGANIZATION JUST FIRST
AND FOREMOST IS IT'S FOUNDED BY VETERANS FOR VETERANS.
IT'S BEEN AROUND FOR 14 YEARS NOW AND YOU KNOW, I THINK THE
BIGGEST THING THAT I CAN SAY TO THE CITY AND COUNTY IS HOW
MEANINGFUL AND IMPACTFUL AND WE DO HAVE A LARGE HOMELESS
VETERAN POPULATION AS WELL AS JUST VETERANS WRIT LARGE.
WE WORK WE WORK A LOT WITH SORTS OF PLOWSHARES WHICH WE
KNOW HAS A DEEP CONNECTION WITH THE CITY.
AND WHAT I WOULD LIKE TO SAY IS JUST THANK YOU AND THE WORK
THAT WE'RE DOING IS IS DEMONSTRATED EVERY SINGLE TIME
WE PUT VETERANS ON THE BOAT. JUST SOME QUICK STATISTICS I'M
SURE YOU GUYS ARE ALL WELL AWARE EVERY 21 SECONDS OF
VETERAN DIES OF SUICIDE IN THE UNITED STATES.
AND YOU KNOW, I THINK A LOT OF THINGS AND YOU CAN SAY WHATEVER
YOU WANT ABOUT THE WARS WE FOUGHT OVER THE LAST 50, 60
YEARS. BUT AT THE END OF THE DAY A LOT
OF THE PEOPLE THAT JOIN WHEN THEY'RE 18, 19 AND 20 HAVE
REALLY NO IDEA WHAT THEY'RE SIGNING UP FOR.
AND YOU KNOW, I THINK THE BIGGEST THING FOR THEM IS
REALLY THE CAMARADERIE THAT THEY COME HOME WITH AND THAT'S
REALLY WHAT WE TRY TO SUPPORT AND REALLY CULTIVATE COMMUNITY
FOR THEM. AND SO I JUST AGAIN JUST WANT
TO SAY THANK YOU. WE ARE HOSTING OUR ANNUAL GALA
ON THE 11TH OF NOVEMBER AT THE ST FRANCIS YACHT CLUB.
WE HAVE THE 31ST CHIEF OF NAVAL OPERATIONS THAT'S GOING TO BE
THERE AS OUR KEYNOTE SPEAKER AND IT'S GOING TO BE A GREAT
EVENING IF YOU WANT TO LEARN MORE ABOUT OUR ORGANIZATION W W
W DOT VETS BOATS DOT ORG WE'RE ALWAYS LOOKING FOR VOLUNTEERS
TO COME ON SAILS WITH US. WE SAIL AT LEAST TWICE A MONTH
AND WE USUALLY HAVE 20 OR 30 VETERANS SHOW UP EITHER FROM VA
FACILITIES THAT WE ARE PARTNERED WITH IN THE CITY OR
IN THE SURROUNDING COMMUNITIES .
AND JUST KIND OF THE LAST PIECE OF INFORMATION YOU KNOW, FOR
EVERY DOLLAR DONATED TO VETS BOATS $0.96 GOES DIRECTLY TO
THE VETERANS TO PUT THEM ON THE WATER.
SO AGAIN, THANK YOU VERY MUCH. MY NAME'S MAC EDELMAN
AND REALLY APPRECIATE YOUR TIME .
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL FIRST ON ROLL
CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS IS SUPERVISOR WANG BUT SINCE HE
STEPPED OUT OF THE CHAMBER WE'LL GO TO SUPERVISOR CHAN WHO
IS ALSO. >> SO SUPERVISOR CHEN, WILL YOU
GO FIRST PLEASE? >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK COLLEAGUES AND IT'S MY HONOR TO
INTRODUCE THIS RESOLUTION COMMENDING KATIE S.F. FOR 50
YEARS OF OUTSTANDING SERVICE TO THE ASIAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
KATIE ASSAF BEGAN BROADCASTING IN SAN FRANCISCO ON SEPTEMBER
4TH, 1976 UNDER FOUNDER LILLIAN LINCOLN HOUSE LEADERSHIP KATIE
S.F. GREW INTO A PIONEER OF MULTI-ETHNIC AND ASIAN LANGUAGE
PROGRAMING IN THE UNITED STATES .
>> IN 1989 KATIE ASSAF LAUNCHED THE FIRST NIGHTLY LIFE CHINESE
LANGUAGE NEWSCAST NEWSCASTS IN CANTONESE IN THE UNITED
STATES IN 1991. IT ADDED LIFE MENTORING
PROGRAMING FOR GENERATIONS OF CHINESE-AMERICAN FAMILIES.
THIS PODCASTS HAVE BEEN A VITAL CONNECTIONS TO VITAL
CONNECTIONS TO LOCAL NEWS COMMUNITY ISSUES
AND INTERNATIONAL EVENTS. KATIE S.F. HAS ALSO PLAYED AN
IMPORTANT ROLE IN HELPING NEW IMMIGRANTS AND LONGTIME
RESIDENTS ALIKE NAVIGATING LIFE IN THE BAY AREA.
IT IS REPORTING AND PUBLIC SERVICES PROGRAMING HAVE
HIGHLIGHTED ISSUES AFFECTING ASIAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITIES
PROVIDING VALUABLE COMMUNITY RESOURCES AND HELP ENSURE THAT
IMPORTANT INFORMATION RICHEST PEOPLE WHO MIGHT OTHERWISE BE
LEFT OUT GIVING THEM THE INFORMATION THEY NEED TO
PARTICIPATE FULLY IN CIVIC LIFE OF OUR CITY.
AS WE CELEBRATE KATIE S.F. 50TH ANNIVERSARY WE RECOGNIZE THE
GENERALISTS, THE BROADCASTERS, STAFF AND COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHO
GIVE OUR COMMUNITIES AN OUTLET FOR OUR STORIES.
THANK YOU TO MY COLLEAGUES WHO HAVE COSPONSORED IT TO
CELEBRATE SEPTEMBER 4TH, 2026 AS KATIE S.F. DAY IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND CONGRATULATION TO KATIE S.F. FOR 50 YEARS OF
EXTRAORDINARY SERVICE. EXTRAORDINARY LEADERSHIP
AND THANK YOU FOR KEEPING OUR COMMUNITIES INFORMED, CONNECTED
AND BE PART OF SAN FRANCISCO STORY.
>> AND THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT THANK
YOU. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE ONE
ORDINANCE AND ONE RESOLUTION FOR INTRODUCTION.
TODAY I'M INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO HELP STEM THE
TIDE OF SAN FRANCISCO'S EVICTION CRISIS.
EVICTIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO HIT A TEN YEAR HIGH LAST YEAR
AND DATA SHOWS THAT WE ARE ON PACE FOR AN EVEN HIGHER NUMBER
OF EVICTIONS THIS YEAR. NONPAYMENT OF RENT IS THE
REASON BEHIND OVER HALF OF RECENT EVICTION PROCEEDINGS
AND THE TRUE NUMBER IS LIKELY EVEN HIGHER AS LANDLORDS ARE
NOT REQUIRED TO REPORT NONPAYMENT EVICTION NOTICES TO
THE RENT BOARD. EVICTION DEFENSE ATTORNEYS
ATTRIBUTE THE RISE IN EVICTIONS TO AN AFFORDABILITY CRISIS.
IN SAN FRANCISCO, RENTS ARE INCREASING AT RECORD HIGH
NUMBERS WHILE A SLOW AND CHALLENGING JOB MARKET FOR
WORKING CLASS RESIDENTS MEANS MANY SAN FRANCISCANS ARE LIVING
PAYCHECK TO PAYCHECK WITH SIGNIFICANT ECONOMIC
UNCERTAINTY. TODAY IN SAN FRANCISCO
LANDLORDS CAN EVICT TENANTS FOR BEING SHORT ANY AMOUNT IN RENT
. LANDLORDS WHO WANT TO TAKE
ADVANTAGE OF A LUCRATIVE RENTAL MARKET LIKE SAN FRANCISCO'S CAN
PURSUE EVICTION AGAINST LONG TIME RENT CONTROLLED TENANTS
WHO HAVE MINUSCULE ONE TIME OR ACCIDENTAL RENT SHORTAGES.
OFTEN TENANTS DO NOT EVEN KNOW THEY HAVE OUTSTANDING RENT OWED
DUE TO A NUMBER OF REASONS INCLUDING THAT THEY'VE BEEN
CHARGED HIDDEN FEES OR HIGHLY VARIABLE UTILITY BILLS WITHOUT
WARNING. IN A REPRESENTATIVE SAMPLE OF
NONPAYMENT EVICTIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO LAST YEAR AROUND 25%
OF TENANTS WERE EVICTED FOR LESS THAN ONE MONTH OF THE FAIR
MARKET RENT FOR THEIR UNIT. THIS IS WHY I'M INTRODUCING
LEGISLATION THAT WILL PREVENT LANDLORDS FROM EVICTING TENANTS
WHO FALL BEHIND IN RENT UNLESS THE TENANT OWES THEM A PORTION
OF THE RENT AN AMOUNT HIGHER THAN THE FAIR MARKET RENT THE
FAIR MARKET RENT DEPENDS ON THE BEDROOM SIZE OF THE RENTAL UNIT
AND IS SET ANNUALLY BY THE DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING AND URBAN
DEVELOPMENT. THIS IS THE SAME STANDARD THAT
IS ALREADY UTILIZED IN CITIES LIKE LOS ANGELES, OAKLAND
AND BERKELEY. THANK YOU TO THE ANTI
DISPLACEMENT COLLECTION INCLUDING THE EVICTION DEFENSE
COLLABORATIVE FOR YOUR WORK WITH US ON THIS AS WELL AS
DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY MANU PRADHAN AND MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE
ANNA HERRERA. I'D ALSO LIKE TO THANK
SUPERVISORS MELGAR WALTON CHAN ,CHEN MAHMOOD AND SADR FOR
YOUR EARLIER CO-SPONSORSHIP. AND I WANT TO THANK THE
MAYOR FOR HIS SUPPORT AS WELL. I LOOK FORWARD TO YOUR SUPPORT
IN THIS LEGISLATION THAT WILL HELP TENANTS ACROSS OUR ENTIRE
CITY. AND TODAY I'M PROUD TO ANNOUNCE
A RESOLUTION DECLARING SEPTEMBER 1ST, 2020 6KLW DAY
IN A CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO IN CELEBRATION OF THE
STATION'S 85TH ANNIVERSARY SINCE 1941.
KUOW 91.7 FM HAS BEEN A FIXTURE OF BAY AREA PUBLIC MEDIA.
IT HAS KEPT JUSTICE, EQUITY AND COMMUNITY STORYTELLING AT
THE CENTER OF ITS WORK WHILE CONTINUALLY EVOLVING TO MEET
THE NEEDS OF ITS LISTENERS. KALE W'S HISTORY OF INNOVATION
SPEAKS FOR ITSELF. IT WAS THE FIRST STATION IN THE
BAY AREA TO AIR PROGRAMS LIKE FRESH AIR THIS AMERICAN LIFE
SNAP JUDGMENT AND THE DAILY. AND THE FIRST TO BRING THE BBC
TO BAY AREA LISTENERS SERVING FOUR DECADES AS THE BBC'S
STATION AND RECORD HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> IT'S ALSO THE BIRTHPLACE OF 99% INVISIBLE AND RADIO ON THE
LAND THE PROGRAMS THAT BUILD ON THE STATION'S TRACK RECORD OF
NURTURING NEW VOICES IN A WAY THAT FEW STATIONS CAN MATCH.
THAT COMMITMENT TO NEW VOICES EXTENDS WELL BEYOND THE STUDIO.
THE ORIGINS OF EAR HUSTLE TRACED DIRECTLY BACK TO CARL
W'S VOLUNTEER PROGRAM AT SAN QUENTIN STATE PRISON A POWERFUL
EXAMPLE OF THE STATION'S DEDICATION TO TELLING STORIES
FROM PLACES THAT ARE TOO OFTEN OVERLOOKED OR SILENCED ENTIRELY
. TODAY KW REMAINS AN ESSENTIAL
AND TRUSTED SOURCE OF NEWS, MUSIC, CULTURE AND COMMUNITY
STORYTELLING THROUGHOUT SAN FRANCISCO IN THE NINE COUNTY
BAY AREA. AS WE MARK THIS 85TH
ANNIVERSARY WE CELEBRATE NOT JUST KUOW WHOSE REMARKABLE
HISTORY BUT LOOK FORWARD TO THE NEXT 85 YEARS OF INDEPENDENT
COMMUNITY POWERED JOURNALISM AND MUSIC.
THANK YOU TO SUPERVISORS WONG CHEN MANAGEMENT AND WALDEN FOR
YOUR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP. THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD. >> SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN THANK YOU,
MADAM. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE TO
MAKE A MINOR ADJUSTMENTS TO THE PLANNING CODE TO EXTEND
ELIGIBILITY FOR LEGAL NONCONFORMING REAR YARD
STRUCTURES TO INCLUDE THOSE CONSTRUCTED BETWEEN 2003 THE
CURRENT CUTOFF AND 2010. THE CHANGE WAS MOTIVATED BY THE
EXPERIENCE OF TWO ELDERLY DISABLED CONSTITUENTS IN MY
DISTRICT. SAM AND MA ARE RETIRED MENTAL
HEALTH PROFESSIONALS HE A MARRIAGE AND FAMILY COUNSELOR.
SHE A LICENSED CLINICAL PSYCHOLOGIST.
THEY SPENT THEIR CAREERS HELPING OTHERS THROUGH CRISIS
AND GRIEF. BUT NOW IN THEIR LATER YEARS
BOTH ARE FACING THEIR OWN PHYSICAL AND MEDICAL
CHALLENGES. FOR THE LAST 18 YEARS SAM
AND MA HAVE MADE DAILY USE OF A MEDITATION ROOM IN THEIR
BACKYARD. THEY BUILT THE ROOM IN 2018 TO
ANCHOR THEIR BUDDHIST PRACTICE. ITS LONG SLOPED EAVES
AND LANTERN STYLE ROOF FOLLOW CENTURIES OLD JAPANESE BUDDHIST
ARCHITECTURAL TRADITION MEANT TO MARK THE PASSAGE INTO A
SPIRITUAL SPACE. ALTHOUGH SALMAN MA, WE'RE TOLD
BY THEIR DESIGNER THAT A PERMIT WOULDN'T BE REQUIRED FOR IT,
THE STRUCTURE NARROWLY EXCEEDS THE SIZE LIMITS FOR REAR YARD
STRUCTURES SET IN THE PLANNING CODE.
>> IN 2019 A DISGRUNTLED NEIGHBOR DENIED A PERMIT OF
THEIR OWN IN THE PROCESS OF SELLING THEIR HOME FILED AN
ANONYMOUS COMPLAINT. NO ONE ELSE ON THE BLOCK HAS
EVER COMPLAINED ABOUT THE STRUCTURE AND LETTERS OF
SUPPORT FOR FOR SAM AND MA HAVE COME FROM EVERY ADJACENT OR
ABUTTING PROPERTY. LAST YEAR, RECOGNIZING THE
PREVALENCE OF LONG STANDING UNPERMITTED REAR YARD
STRUCTURES IN NEIGHBORHOODS ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO, THIS
BOARD PASSED LEGISLATION TO LEGALIZE NONCONFORMING REAR
YARD STRUCTURES BUILT BEFORE 2003.
>> THIS LEGISLATION WOULD CHANGE THAT DATE TO 2010 TO
ACCOMMODATE SALMON MA'S MEDITATION SPACE AND OTHER
SIMILAR NONCONFORMING STRUCTURES CONSTRUCTED BEFORE
2010. I WANT TO THANK LISA GLUCKSTEIN
AND ELIZABETH WATTY FOR HELPING US FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
FOR HELPING US FIND THE SOLUTION.
I WANT TO THANK ROB COPPOLA FOR THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE FOR
HIS WORK AND MY AIDE RENE AUBERJONOIS FOR HIS WORK
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SAUDER THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> COLLEAGUES AT THE BEGINNING OF THIS YEAR I ASKED THE BUDGET
AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYSTS TO INVENTORY AND REPORT ON
OPPORTUNITIES FOR USING VACANT OR SURPLUS CITY AND PUBLIC
PROPERTIES FOR HOUSING AND OTHER PUBLIC PURPOSES.
AND AT MY REQUEST BIELA HAS SPENT THE PAST SEVERAL MONTHS
CONDUCTING A REVIEW OF PUBLICLY OWNED PROPERTIES ACROSS THE
CITY WITH THE GOAL OF IDENTIFYING PROPERTIES WITH
POTENTIAL FOR DEVELOPMENT, SECONDARY USES OR JOINT
DEVELOPMENT USING SPECIFIC EVALUATION CRITERIA.
THEY CANVASED 30 CITY DEPARTMENTS AGENCIES
AND EDUCATIONAL ENTITIES INCLUDING S.F. USD AND CITY
COLLEGE. >> THEY EXAMINED WELL OVER 100
PROPERTIES REPRESENTING APPROXIMATELY SIX POINT
2,000,000FT2 OF PUBLIC LAND. THEY APPLIED A HIGH LEVEL
PRELIMINARY SCREENING BASED ON CRITERIA SUCH AS BEING IN POOR
OR DEFICIENT CONDITION, HAVING EXCESS LAND OR LOW SITE
UTILIZATION. THIS ALL GIVES US PRELIMINARY
RESULTS FOR PROPERTIES THAT WARRANT FURTHER EVALUATION.
NOW WE EXPECT THE FULL REPORT TO BE PUBLISHED IN THE COMING
DAYS BUT I'M HAPPY TO SHARE THAT THERE'S A LOT OF SUBSTANCE
IN WHAT THE BLR FOUND. PUT ANOTHER WAY.
WE'RE CLEARLY SITTING ON A TREMENDOUS RESOURCE THAT WE
NEED TO USE BETTER. FOR EXAMPLE, THE REPORT WILL
SHOW THAT THERE ARE 44 VACANT OR SOON TO BE VACANT PROPERTIES
THAT MAY WARRANT FURTHER EVALUATION FOR AFFORDABLE
HOUSING OR OTHER DEVELOPMENT OPPORTUNITIES AND USING
SPECIFIC SITE THE REPORT SPECIFIC SITES.
THE REPORT CONTEMPLATES THE NUMBER OF UNITS OF HOUSING THAT
MIGHT BE PRODUCED ON VACANT OR UNDERUTILIZED LAND AND SHOWS
THAT THIS NUMBER QUICKLY REACHES MANY THOUSANDS OF NEW
HOMES. >> THE REPORT ALSO ALSO PUSHES
US TO BE MORE THOUGHTFUL ON HOW WE ORGANIZE OUR SPACE.
SETTING AN EXAMPLE WHERE S.F. USED HAS ADMINISTRATIVE
FUNCTIONS SPREAD ACROSS EIGHT DIFFERENT PROPERTIES.
>> MOVING FROM THIS ANALYSIS TO ACTION WILL TAKE FURTHER
RESEARCH AND DISCUSSION BUT MOST OF ALL IT WILL TAKE
COORDINATION AND LEADERSHIP. AND THE BLM REPORT WILL CLEARLY
LAY OUT WHY THE CURRENT PROCESS OR LACK OF ONE FOR SHORT
THERE'S NO TRUE OWNER OR VISION FOR THIS PROCESS.
INSTEAD IT IS LEFT TODAY TO A PIECEMEAL APPROACH AND IS
FRAGMENTED HEAVILY BY DEPARTMENT.
NOW THE GOOD NEWS IS THAT ONE CITY AGENCY HAS OPTED FOR A
MORE SYSTEMATIC APPROACH TO EVALUATING THEIR REAL ESTATE
PORTFOLIO. THE MTA, FOR EXAMPLE, THROUGH
ITS JOINT DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM IS PROACTIVELY SEEKING TO
IDENTIFY PROPERTIES TO GENERATE REVENUE, MODERNIZE
TRANSPORTATION FACILITIES AND SUPPORT HOUSING PRODUCTION.
BUT THAT BEGS THE QUESTION WHY ISN'T THIS BEING DONE AT EVERY
DEPARTMENT OR ON A CITYWIDE SCALE LEVEL?
SO WITH THE BLAZE LAND REPORT ON OUR UNDERUTILIZED PROPERTY
IS BEING PUBLISHED IN THE COMING DAYS, I AM TODAY
SUBMITTING A HEARING REQUEST TO DISCUSS THE BLAZE FINDING
AND POLICY OPTIONS WITH THE DEPARTMENT OF REAL ESTATE.
THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT, THE
OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT
AND THE S.F. MTA TO REPORT. >> IT IS CLEAR THAT WE NEED A
CITYWIDE DIRECTION AND COORDINATE THAT LONG TERM
APPROACH TO LEVERAGING PUBLICLY OWNED PARCELS TO MEET THE MOST
CRITICAL NEEDS OF SAN FRANCISCANS AND I LOOK FORWARD
TO HAVING THIS CONVERSATION AND DOING THE WORK TO CHART A
PATH FORWARD. THE ASSESSMENT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SAUTER SUPERVISOR
CHERYL SUBMIT THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE ONE
IN MEMORIAM. I AM HONORING THE LIFE
AND LEGACY OF VIVIAN AND HOPKINS, A TRUE DAUGHTER OF
SAN FRANCISCO. VIVIAN WAS RAISED IN PATROL
HILL AND GRADUATED FROM MISSION HIGH SCHOOL IN 1970.
SHE CARRIED WITH HER THROUGHOUT HER LIFE THE VALUES SHE LEARNED
FROM HER MOTHER AND GRANDMOTHER HARD WORK, DETERMINATION,
INTEGRITY AND A DEEP COMMITMENT TO COMMUNITY.
VIVIAN BUILT AN EXTRAORDINARY CAREER SPANNING
ENTREPRENEURSHIP CORPORATE LEADERSHIP, NONPROFIT FOOD
SERVICE AND PUBLIC ADMINISTRATION.
>> SHE BROUGHT HER TALENT FOR ORGANIZING PROBLEM SOLVING
AND BRINGING PEOPLE TOGETHER TO ORGANIZATIONS INCLUDING YOUNG
COMMUNITY DEVELOPERS AND THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. >> AS PROJECT MANAGER FOR S.F.
SHINES, SHE HELPED INVEST IN SMALL BUSINESSES
AND REVITALIZE COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS WHILE HONORING THE
HISTORY AND LEGACY OF THE COMMUNITIES SHE SERVED.
BUT VIVIAN'S GREATEST IMPACT CANNOT BE MEASURED BY A TITLE
OR A JOB DESCRIPTION. SHE HAD A GIFT FOR USING HER
KNOWLEDGE, RELATIONSHIPS AND INFLUENCE TO OPEN DOORS FOR
OTHERS. SHE KNEW HOW TO GET THINGS DONE
AND SHE GENUINELY WANTED PEOPLE AND COMMUNITIES TO SUCCEED.
THOSE WHO KNEW VIVIAN WELL REMEMBER HER BRIGHT SMILE, HER
LAUGH, HER HONESTY AND HER WILLINGNESS TO TELL YOU EXACTLY
WHAT SHE THOUGHT. SHE LOVED HER FAMILY DEEPLY
AND SHE LOVED GOOD FOOD, TRAVEL, LAUGHTER AND BRINGING
PEOPLE TOGETHER. HER LEGENDARY HOLIDAY MEALS
WERE AN EXPRESSION OF THAT LOVE AND GENEROSITY.
VIVIAN TRAVELED THE WORLD BUT SAN FRANCISCO WAS ALWAYS HOME.
SHE GAVE SO MUCH TO THIS CITY AND TO THE PEOPLE WHO WERE
FORTUNATE ENOUGH TO KNOW HER. I EXTEND MY DEEPEST CONDOLENCES
TO VIVIAN'S DAUGHTERS. GRANDCHILDREN, GREAT
GRANDCHILDREN, EXTENDED FAMILY AND COUNTLESS FRIENDS
AND COLLEAGUES. MAY WE HONOR VIVIAN BY
REMEMBERING THE LIGHT SHE BROUGHT INTO OUR LIVES THE
COMMUNITIES SHE STRENGTHENED AND THE OPPORTUNITIES SHE
CREATED FOR OTHERS. AND MAY HER EXTRAORDINARY
LEGACY LIVE ON. >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> SUPERVISOR WANG. COLLEAGUES, I AM INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION TO SUPPORT CONGRESSMEMBER KEVIN MULLINS
AVE EMERGENCY RESPONSE COORDINATION ACT.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN ON THE FRONT LINES OF AUTONOMOUS
VEHICLE DEPLOYMENT AND WE'VE ALSO SEEN FIRSTHAND WHAT CAN
HAPPEN WHEN THESE VEHICLES ENCOUNTER EXTRAORDINARY
CIRCUMSTANCES. DURING LAST DECEMBER'S MAJOR
PGA AND EE POWER OUTAGE AND AGAIN FOLLOWING THE 4TH OF
JULY FIREWORKS, AUTONOMOUS VEHICLES BECAME STRANDED AND IN
SOME CASES INTERFERED WITH TRAFFIC AND EMERGENCY
OPERATIONS. THIS LEGISLATION TAKES A
PRACTICAL APPROACH. IT WOULD ESTABLISH CLEAR
NATIONAL STANDARDS FOR COMMUNICATION OF FIRST
RESPONDERS REQUIRED A 24 HOUR EMERGENCY HOTLINE AND ALLOW
PUBLIC AGENCIES TO QUICKLY GEOFENCE AREAS DURING
EMERGENCIES AND MAJOR EVENTS. AUTONOMOUS VEHICLES ARE HERE TO
STAY. WE NEED TO MAKE SURE INNOVATION
GOES HAND IN HAND WITH PUBLIC SAFETY AND THAT OUR FIRST
RESPONDERS HAVE THE TOOLS THEY NEED WHEN SOMETHING GOES WRONG.
I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF
ASSEMBLYMEMBER KATHRYN STEPHANIE'S A.B. 2540, THE
COMMUNITY COLLEGE STUDENT RIGHT TO ACCESS ACT.
>> CALIFORNIA ALREADY REQUIRES YOU AND CSU CAMPUSES TO PROVIDE
MEDICATION ABORTION BUT COMMUNITY COLLEGE STUDENTS WERE
LEFT OUT OF THAT LAW. THAT CREATES AN UNNECESSARY
DISPARITY, PARTICULARLY FOR STUDENTS WHO MAY ALSO BE
BALANCING WORK, CAREGIVING AND FACING FINANCIAL
CHALLENGES. HB 2540 WOULD CLOSE THAT GAP BY
EXPANDING ACCESS THROUGH HUMAN COLLEGE HEALTH CENTERS,
TELEHEALTH OR PARTNERSHIPS WITH OUTSIDE PROVIDERS WHILE
PROVIDING FLEXIBILITY BASED ON EACH CAMPUSES CAPACITY.
>> CITY COLLEGE OF SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALREADY ENDORSED
THIS LEGISLATION AS A PASSPORT PRESIDENT FOR THE CITY COLLEGE
BOARD TRUSTEES. I BELIEVE IT'S IMPORTANT FOR
SAN FRANCISCO TO TAKE A STANCE AND SUPPORT THIS AS WELL.
THIS RESOLUTION ADDS SAN FRANCISCO SUPPORT AND CALLS FOR
ADEQUATE STATE FUNDING SO THESE SERVICES CAN BE IMPLEMENTED
WITHOUT TAKING RESOURCES AWAY FROM OTHER STUDENT HEALTH NEEDS
. FINALLY TODAY I'M ASKING THE
CITY ATTORNEY TO BEGIN DRAFTING LEGISLATION TO UPDATE SAN
FRANCISCO'S FORMULA RETAIL RULES.
OUR RETAIL LANDSCAPE HAS CHANGED DRAMATICALLY IN RECENT
YEARS ACROSS THE CITY. WE'RE SEEING PERSISTENT
STOREFRONT VACANCIES CHANGING SHOPPING PATTERNS AND SPACES
SITTING EMPTY FOR EXTENDED PERIODS OF TIME.
AT THE SAME TIME, SAN FRANCISCO'S FORMULA RETAIL
REGULATIONS CAN MAKE IT MORE DIFFICULT FOR CERTAIN
BUSINESSES TO OPEN EVEN IN LOCATIONS WHERE A STOREFRONT
MAY BE DOING MORE HARM THAN A NEW TENANT WOULD.
I THINK IT'S TIME WE UPDATE THESE RULES TO BETTER REFLECT
TODAY'S ECONOMIC REALITY MAKE IT EASIER TO FILL VACANT
STOREFRONTS AND BRING MORE FOOT TRAFFIC AND ACTIVITIES BACK TO
OUR STREETS. >> THEIR ASSESSMENT.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WONG SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
OFFICIALLY INTRODUCING A PAIR OF LEGISLATION THE SMALL
BUSINESS TENANTS UNION AND THE WORKERS OPPORTUNITY TO PURCHASE
ACT TODAY. >> THE LEGISLATION WITHIN
TENSION TO EMPOWER OUR SMALL BUSINESSES AND CREATE
ENTREPRENEURSHIP OPPORTUNITIES AND JOB SECURITY FOR WORKERS.
OVER THE LAST FEW YEARS AS THE COST OF LIVING AND MARKET
SPECULATION RISES, WE HAVE CONTINUED TO HEAR STORIES ABOUT
LONG TIME SMALL BUSINESSES GETTING FORCED OUT.
FACING THE SAME CHALLENGES AS TENANTS RESIDENTIAL TENANTS
IN SAN FRANCISCO HIGH RENT THREATS OF EVICTION
UNREASONABLE LEASE TERM DISPLACEMENT AND CORPORATE
TAKEOVER. >> WHEN A LOCAL BUSINESS
CLOSES, THE NEIGHBORHOOD CLOSES AND WORKERS ARE FORCED INTO
UNEMPLOYMENT. THE SMALL BUSINESS TENANTS
UNION'S IS A LEGISLATION THAT MODEL AFTER THE SUCCESSFUL
UNION AT HOME LEGISLATION AND JAPANTOWN MA MERCHANTS
ORGANIZING. THIS LEGISLATION WILL EMPOWER
SMALL COMMERCIAL TENANTS TO UNIONIZE IN ORDER TO BARGAIN
WITH COMMERCIAL PROPERTY LANDLORDS AND MANAGEMENT
AND PROHIBIT PROPERTY OWNERS FROM BANNING BUSINESS OWNERS
FROM ORGANIZING IN THEIR PLACES OF BUSINESS.
THIS ORDINANCE ALSO ALLOWS THE CITY TO RECOGNIZE THESE UNION
ORGANIZATION AS SO THEY CAN RECEIVE SUPPORT.
IT WILL ALSO REALLY SUPPORT AND BOOST THE BUSINESS OWNERS
ABILITY SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS ABILITY TO LEVEL THE FIELD
AND PREVENT DISPLACEMENT WHEN THEY WORK TOGETHER TO NEGOTIATE
BUSINESS CONDITIONS. SECOND, THE WORKERS OPPORTUNITY
TO PURCHASE ACT IS MODELED AFTER THE LANDMARK COMMUNITY
OPPORTUNITY TO PURCHASE ACT ALSO KNOWN AS COPA.
THE LEGISLATION WILL INCENTIVIZE OWNERS TO CONSIDER
A SUCCESSION PLAN AND SELL THEIR BUSINESS TO THE WORKERS
WHO ALREADY KNOW THE BUSINESS OPERATION.
IT WILL EMPOWER WORKERS TO BECOME ENTREPRENEURS THEMSELVES
THROUGH A WORKER CO-OP. THE ORDINANCE WILL REQUIRE
ADVANCE NOTICE TO WORKERS WHEN OWNERS WANT TO SELL THEIR
BUSINESS AND PROVIDE WORKERS WITH THE RIGHT TO FIRST OFFER
WHICH ALLOWS EMPLOYEES A PERIOD OF TIME TO FORM A WORKER CO-OP
IN ORDER TO EXPRESS INTEREST IN MAKING AN OFFER TO PURCHASE
THE BUSINESS. IF INTEREST EXISTS TO FORM A
WORKER CO-OP, THE GROUP IS ALLOW ADDITIONAL TIME TO
FINALIZE FINANCES AND SUBMIT AN INFORMAL OFFER.
ALTHOUGH ANY OWNERS RETAIN THE RIGHT TO REJECT OFFER
AND WORKER CO-OPS WILL HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO MATCH OR COUNTER
OTHER OFFERS. >> OUR CITY AND OUR COMMUNITIES
THRIVE WHEN OUR SMALL BUSINESSES AND WORKERS THRIVE.
I LIKE TO THANK JAPANTOWN MERCHANTS FOR THE INSPIRATION
FOR SMALL BUSINESS TENANTS UNION AND ALSO HOPE WILLIAMS
AND PAULA EISNER FROM SUSTAINABLE ECONOMIES LAW
CENTER AND BENJIE KAPLAN FROM UFC W LOCAL FIVE FOR THEIR
COLLABORATION ON DRAFTING THIS PIECE OF LEGISLATION.
>> LAST BUT NOT LEAST COLLEAGUES, I'M ALSO
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION URGING THE CALIFORNIA ENVIRONMENTAL
PROTECTION AGENCY AND THE OFFICE OF ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH
HAZARD ASSESSMENT TO REFINE THE CAO ENVIRO SCREEN FRAMEWORK TO
ENSURE DENSE, LOW INCOME URBAN NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE BAYVIEW
HUNTERS POINT, CHINATOWN MISSION, SALTON MARKET
AND TENDERLOIN. REACHING OPPORTUNITIES TO
ESSENTIAL STATE GRANTS USING ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH
AND SOCIOECONOMIC INFORMATION. CAO EPA DEVELOP CAO IN VIA
ENVIRO SCREEN TO IDENTIFY COMMUNITIES BURDENED BY
MULTIPLE SOURCES OF POLLUTION AND POPULATION VULNERABILITIES.
COMMUNITIES DESIGN AS DISADVANTAGED WHICH ARE
ELIGIBLE FOR CRITICAL FUNDING STREAMS TO SUPPORT PROGRAMS TO
ADDRESS ENVIRONMENTAL CONCERNS INCLUDING SENATE BILL 535.
>> GREENHOUSE GAS REDUCTION FUNDS ENVIRONMENTAL REMEDY
REMEDY REMEDY ACTION GRANT URBAN GREENING ALLOCATIONS
AND PUBLIC HEALTH INFRASTRUCTURE INVESTMENT.
>> THE JULY 2026 VERSION OF THE CAO ENVIRO SCREEN AFTER SCORING
THRESHOLDS IN WAYS THAT WOULD REMOVE CERTAIN DENSE LOW INCOME
URBAN NEIGHBORHOODS FROM THE LIST OF DISADVANTAGED
COMMUNITIES THEREBY THUS ALLOWING LOCAL PUBLIC AGENCIES
AND COMMUNITY BASED ORGANIZATIONS FROM APPLYING FOR
AND RECEIVING STATE GRANT FUNDS THAT LOW INCOME RESIDENTS
DESPERATELY LEE RE RELY ON FOR DECARBONIZATION INFRASTRUCTURE
KARCHER INDOOR AIR FILTRATION. URBAN COOLING AND LOCAL TRANSIT
EQUITY RESOLUTION URGE CAO EPA TO SUSPEND ANY PROPOSED METRIC
UPDATES THAT WOULD STRIP GRANT ELIGIBILITY FROM HISTORICALLY
VULNERABLE URBAN CENSUS TRACT UNTIL A ROBUST CONSULTATION
OCCURS WITH RESIDENTS, COMMUNITY ADVOCATES
AND ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE ORGANIZATION IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND WITH THAT THE REST I WILL SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN.
MR. PRESIDENT, SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER THAT CONCLUDES
THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS.
>> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL
ORDER PLEASE CALL ITEMS 25 THROUGH 28 TOGETHER.
>> ITEMS 25 THROUGH 28 COMPRISE THE PUBLIC HEARING OF PERSONS
INTERESTED IN THE DECISION OF PUBLIC WORKS DATED AUGUST 6TH
2026 TO APPROVE A TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP FOR A TWO UNIT
CONDOMINIUM CONVERSION PROJECT AT 2722 THROUGH 2724 FOLSOM
STREET. ITEM 26 THIS IS THE MOTION TO
APPROVE THE PUBLIC WORKS DECISION AND TO APPROVE THE
TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
ENVIRONMENTAL FINDINGS. ITEM 27 THIS IS THE MOTION TO
CONDITIONALLY DISAPPROVE THE PUBLIC WORKS DECISION
AND DISAPPROVE THE TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP SUBJECT TO THE
BOARD'S ADOPTION OF WRITTEN FINDINGS IN SUPPORT OF THE
DISAPPROVAL. AND ITEM 28 IS THE MOTION TO
DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS RELATED TO THE BOARD'S
DECISION TO DISAPPROVE OF THE TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP FOR THE
PROJECT. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
WE HAVE BEFORE US AN APPEAL OF THE TENTATIVE PARTIAL MAP
APPROVAL BY PUBLIC WORKS FOR THE PROJECT AT 2722 TO 2724
FOLSOM STREET. AFTER THE HEARING THE BOARD
WILL VOTE ON WHETHER TO APPROVE OR CONDITIONALLY DISAPPROVE THE
DECISION OF PUBLIC WORKS. >> MOST THEIR OBJECTIONS WE
WILL PROCEED AS FOLLOWS UP TO TEN MINUTES FOR A PRESENTATION
BY THE APPELLANT. ALSO THE PROJECT SPONSOR.
THEN THERE WILL BE PUBLIC COMMENT OF TWO MINUTES PER
SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL.
THEN WE WILL HEAR A PRESENTATION OF UP TO TEN
MINUTES FROM THE CITY DEPARTMENTS.
AGAIN THERE WILL BE PUBLIC COMMENT TWO MINUTES PER SPEAKER
IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL. AND FINALLY WILL HAVE UP TO
THREE MINUTES FOR REBUTTAL BY THE APPELLANTS.
>> I DON'T SEE ANY OBJECTIONS SO SEEING NO OBJECTIONS.
>> THE PUBLIC HEARING WILL PROCEED AS INDICATED AND IS NOW
OPEN AND WE WILL NOW HEAR FROM THE APPELLANT WHO HAS UP TO TEN
MINUTES. >> ANYONE THERE IS I GOT IT.
>> YOU MAY BEGIN. YES, MR. RAY, CAN YOU MAKE SURE
YOU SPEAK DIRECTLY INTO THE MICROPHONE?
>> OF COURSE. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
MEMBERS OF THE BOARD SAMUEL RAY FOR THE OWNERS OF 272222724
FOLSOM STREET. TO BE CLEAR, THE OWNERS ARE NOT
APPEALING THE APPROVED COUNT OF A CONVERSION MAP.
INSTEAD THEY APPEAL THE CONDITIONS IMPOSED AND ADDED BY
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT IN THEIR REFERRAL FORM WHICH IS
ON PAGE 180 OF THE BOARD'S PACKET.
AT THE CONCLUSION OF THIS MY PRESENTATION I WILL ASK THE
BOARD TO SUSTAIN THE APPEAL AND CONDITIONALLY DENY THE
TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP AND ADOPT WRITTEN FINDINGS INDICATING
THAT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT ADDED CONDITIONS SHOULD NOT
HAVE BEEN INCLUDED. THIS PROPERTY WAS A SUBJECT OF
LITIGATION BETWEEN THE CITY AND THE OWNERS IN FEDERAL COURT
PERTAINING TO THE CITY'S CLAIMED EXISTENCE OF AN ALLEGED
UNDUE OR UNAUTHORIZED ONE UNIT. THAT LITIGATION WAS RESOLVED BY
A SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT IN DECEMBER OF 2025 WHICH WAS
APPROVED BY THIS BOARD AS ORDINANCE NUMBER 2912 4
IN 2023. THE OWNERS ATTEMPTED TO CONVERT
THE PROPERTY. THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS
SENT A REFERRAL TO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT IN AUGUST OF 2023.
INITIALLY THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT DECLINED TO RESPOND
WITHIN THE REQUIRED 30 DAYS SIGNED INTO A LITIGATION HOLD
DUE TO THE PENDING LITIGATION. WHEN THE PENDING LITIGATION WAS
RESOLVED, THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT WAITED ANOTHER 3017
MONTHS TO PROVIDE THE REFERRAL AND ONLY DID SO AFTER THE OWNER
SENT A LETTER DEMANDING THAT THE HOLD BE LIFTED.
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT INITIALLY PROVIDED A REFERRAL
ON MAY 28TH, 2026 WHICH INCLUDED TWO CONDITIONS.
THIS APPEAL WAS FILED ON AUGUST 14TH, 2026 AND ABOUT TEN
MINUTES AFTER THE APPEAL WAS FILED THE CITY PROVIDED THE
OWNERS WITH AN UPDATED REFERRAL FROM PLANNING WHICH REMOVED ONE
OF THE CONDITIONS AT ISSUE AND THEN UPDATED REFERRALS.
PAGE 180 OF THE BOARD'S PACKET THE REMAINING CONDITION AT
ISSUE STATES THAT NO FINAL MAP MAY BE APPROVED OR RECORDED
UNTIL ALL PLANNING CODE VIOLATIONS AT THE PROPERTY ARE
FULLY ABATED. THE OWNERS NOW APPEAL THAT
CONDITION AS HAVING NO BASIS FIRST IN THE LAW AND SECOND
IN THE FACTS. >> THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
AUTHORITY TO CONDITION A FINAL MAP IS FOUND IN SUBDIVISION
CODE SECTION 1326 AND 1327 WHICH PROVIDES THAT THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT CAN RECOMMEND CONDITIONS OF
APPROVAL WITHIN 30 DAYS OF A REQUEST BY DPW.
>> HERE THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT WAITED THREE YEARS TO PROVIDE
CONDITIONS OF APPROVAL CITING A LITIGATION HOLD THAT HAD LONG
CEASED TO EXIST. FURTHER, THE AUTHORITY'S CITED
BY THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT IN THE REFERRAL NAMELY
SUBDIVISION CODE 1383 AND PLANNING CODE 174 AND 176
HAVE NO APPLICATION TO THE PROPERTY FIRST SECTION 1383
FOUND IN ARTICLE NINE OF THE PLAN OF THE SUBDIVISION CODE
DOES NOT APPLY TO TWO UNIT DWELLINGS.
THAT'S EXPLICITLY STATED IN SECTION 1359 C OF THE
SUBDIVISION CODE. LIKEWISE PLANNING CODE SECTION
174 AND 176 HAVE NO RELEVANCE AS THERE ARE NO EXISTING
NOTICES OF VIOLATION AT THE PROPERTY NOR ARE THEIR
CONDITIONS STIPULATIONS, SPECIAL RESTRICTIONS OR
LIMITATIONS IMPOSED BY AN ADMINISTRATIVE ACTION THAT
WOULD IMPACT THE OWNER'S RIGHT TO CANNOT CONVERT.
AS SUCH, THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT PROCEEDED WITHOUT
ANY AUTHORITY TO ACQUIRE THE CONDITION AND IT'S IMPORTANT TO
EMPHASIZE THAT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAS NEVER ISSUED ANY
VIOLATIONS AGAINST THE PROPERTY RELATED TO THE ALLEGED
UNAUTHORIZED ONE UNIT. >> FIRST, THAT'S CLEAR FROM THE
CITY'S OWN RECORDS INCLUDING THE THREE HOUR REPORT WHICH IS
PAGE 12 AND 14 OF YOUR PACKET. >> THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S
PROPERTY INFORMATION MAP SHOWING NO NOTICES OF VIOLATION
WHICH IS ON PAGE 37 OF THIS BOARD'S PACKET AND AS WELL AS
THE DECLARATION OF ONE OF THE OWNERS MICHAEL TERAN WHICH IS
PAGE 39 TO 40 OF THE BOARD'S PACKET.
FURTHER I'D ENCOURAGE THE BOARD TO ASK THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
WHETHER THE THEY EVER ISSUED A NOTICE OF VIOLATION RELATED TO
THE UNAUTHORIZED ONE UNIT. YET PLANNING'S BRIEF AGAINST
THIS APPEAL STATES THAT THE UDC WAS CONFIRMED AND THAT'S ON
PAGE TWO AND SIX OF THEIR BRIEF AND AS A BASIS FOR THAT THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT REFERS TO THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT IN THE
FEDERAL CASE AS WELL AS THE SUSPENSION OF A BUILDING PERMIT
AT THE PROPERTY WHICH WAS PART OF THE UNDERLYING FACTS OF THE
LITIGATION. NONE OF THESE DOCUMENTS
SUBSTANTIATE THE EXISTENCE OF THE ALLEGED UNAUTHORIZED ONE
UNIT. FIRST, THE PERMIT DISCUSSION
PERTAINED TO A DISCREPANCY IN THE FLOOR PLAN LAYOUT
AND MAKES NO REFERENCE TO THE EXISTENCE OF A UDL.
NEXT THE ISSUE OF THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT OR SORRY
THE ISSUE OF THE UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNIT WAS NEVER FULLY
AGREED UPON IN THE FEDERAL LITIGATION OR IN THE
CORRESPONDING SETTLEMENT. INSTEAD THE FEDERAL LITIGATION
WAS RESOLVED BY WAY OF THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT APPROVED
BY THIS BOARD IN WHICH THE OWNERS AND THE CITY REACHED AN
AGREEMENT ON A PATHWAY FORWARD WITHOUT EVER AGREEING WHETHER
THE UDU DID OR DID NOT EXIST. THAT SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT IS
EXHIBIT H WHICH BEGINS ON 54 OF THE SPORTS PACKET
AND IMPORTANTLY ARTICLE SIX OF THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT
EXPLICITLY PROHIBITS CONDITIONING OF THIS KIND OF
CONVERSION ON FULFILLMENT OF THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENTS TERMS
. THAT'S PAGE 62 OF THE BOARD'S
PACKET. YET IT'S CLEAR FROM THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S BRIEF WHICH REFERENCES THE SETTLEMENT
AGREEMENT AS A BASIS THAT THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT THEY'RE
TRYING TO DO BY WAY OF THIS CONDITION.
AND TO BE CLEAR, THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAD THE OPTION TO
CHECK ONE OF THREE BOXES ON THE REFERRAL.
THE FIRST BOX DID NOT CHECK IS CONSISTENT WITH THE TERMS OF
THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT SPECIFICALLY ARTICLE SIX.
INSTEAD THEY CHECKED THE SECOND BOX WHICH CONDITIONED THE
SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT ON NONEXISTENT CODE VIOLATIONS.
>> THEREFORE THERE'S NO LEGAL BASIS FOR THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S CONDITION NOR IS THERE A FACTUAL BASIS
SUPPORTING THE EXISTENCE OF ANY NOTICE OF THE VIOLATION AT THE
PROPERTY AS NONE HAVE BEEN ISSUED BY THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT. THEREFORE THE CONDITION IS
LEGALLY AND FACTUALLY IMPROPER AND RUNS AFOUL OF ARTICLE SIX
OF THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT. THEREFORE WE ASKED THIS BOARD
TO SUSTAIN THE APPEAL TO CONDITIONALLY DENY TENTATIVE
PARTIAL MAP 1 TO 1 ZERO THREE AND ADOPT WRITTEN FINDINGS
INDICATING THAT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S ADDED CONDITION
SHOULD NOT BE INCLUDED AND INSTEAD TO CHECK THE FIRST
BOX ON THE REFERRAL FORM INSTEAD OF THE SECOND BOX
CONDITION IN THE OF CONVERSION. THANK YOU.
>> ARE THERE ANY QUESTIONS? I DON'T SEE ANY QUESTIONS.
THANK YOU. SO WE WILL NOW OPEN PUBLIC
COMMENT. >> UP TO TWO MINUTES A SPEAKER
IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL. ALL RIGHT.
FOR THOSE OF YOU WHO ARE HERE TO SPEAK ON BEHALF OF THE
APPELLANT OR IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT
HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER SEEING NO TAKERS.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, WE WILL GO TO THE REMOTE SYSTEM TO MY STAFF.
HAS ANYONE JOINED REMOTELY FOR THIS PART OF THE HEARING?
>> RECHECKING, MR. PRESIDENT? NO.
>> NO. THERE ARE ZERO CALLERS.
ALL RIGHT. SO PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF
THE APPEAL IS NOW CLOSED AND WE WILL NOW HEAR FOR UP TO TEN
MINUTES FROM REPRESENTATIVES OF CITY DEPARTMENTS.
>> HELLO. MY NAME IS ELIAS FRENCH AND I
AM CITY AND COUNTY SURVEYOR AND MANAGER OF THE BUREAU OF
SURVEYING AND MAPPING SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC WORKS.
THANK YOU CHAIR MANAGEMENT AND SUPERVISORS FOR THIS CHANCE
TO RESPOND TO THE APPEAL. >> OUR OFFICE PROCESSES ALL
SUBDIVISION APPLICATIONS IN THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I COULD RESPOND TO THE APPEAL ON BEHALF OF PUBLIC WORKS.
>> THE APPLICATION PROPOSED A TWO UNIT CONDO CONVERSION OF
272222 7 TO 4 FOLSOM STREET. IT WAS SUBMITTED SEPTEMBER
23RD, 2023 CONDITIONALLY APPROVED BY CITY PLANNING MAY
28TH 2026 AND APPROVED AGAIN BY PLANNING WITH REVISED
CONDITIONS ON AUGUST 4TH, 2026. >> OUR OFFICE ISSUED AN
OFFICIAL TENTATIVE MAP APPROVAL ON AUGUST 5TH.
TENTATIVE APPROVAL WAS ISSUED BY EMAIL TO THE PROJECT'S
SURVEYOR. WE WERE LATER NOTIFIED THAT THE
OWNER HAD NOT YET RECEIVED THE APPROVAL DOCUMENTS AND SO I
EMAILED IT TO THEM ON AUGUST 14TH.
>> I UNDERSTAND THEY NOW HAVE IT.
THE APPEALS SITE'S CONCERNS RELATED TO PROCESSING TIMELINES
AND THE EXISTENCE OF PLANNING VIOLATIONS.
WE WILL DEFER TO PLANNING TO RESPOND TO THOSE.
IT ALSO DISPUTES THE APPLICATION OF SUBDIVISION CODE
SECTION 1383. THIS CODE REQUIRES ALL
APPLICABLE PROVISIONS OF CITY HOUSING BUILDING AND PLANNING
TO BE MET AND ANY VIOLATION CAN BE CORRECTED PRIOR TO FINAL MAP
APPROVAL. >> THERE IS ALSO AN OPTION
SUBJECT TO APPROVAL BY THE DIRECTOR FOR APPLICANTS TO
DEFER ANY CORRECTIVE WORK. IF FUNDS TO COMPLETE IT ARE
BONDED THE APPEAL ARGUES IT IS IMPROPER TO APPLY 1383 BECAUSE
IT RESIDES IN ARTICLE NINE OF THE SUBDIVISION CODE AND PER
THAT SAME CODE SECTION 1359 SEE TWO UNIT OWNER OCCUPIED
CONVERSIONS ARE EXEMPT FROM ARTICLE NINE.
>> I CAN ADDRESS THAT ARGUMENT. >> OUR OFFICE DISAGREES WITH
THIS POSITION. WE HAVE APPLIED THE SUBSTANCE
OF SECTION 1383 TO ALL CONDO CONVERSIONS FOR MANY YEARS.
WE SUPPORT THIS PRACTICE FOR SEVERAL REASONS.
WE ALSO ACKNOWLEDGE THE OBSERVATION THE APPELLANT MADE
THAT THIS SECTION IS CONTAINED IN ARTICLE NINE FROM WHICH THIS
PROJECT IS EXEMPT PER CODE. THIS DOES NOT AFFECT THE
NECESSITY TO APPLY THESE REQUIREMENTS.
>> THE SUBSTANCE OF SECTION 1383 ARTICLE NINE PRIMARILY
DEALS I'LL ADDRESS THE ARTICLE NINE EXEMPTION ISSUE.
>> ARTICLE NINE PRIMARILY DEALS WITH RULES FOR THE CONDO
CONVERSION LOTTERY AND THE EXPEDITED CONVERSION PROGRAM.
>> OUR POSITION IS THAT THE INTENT OF THE EXEMPTION FOR A
TWO UNIT OWNER OCCUPIED BUILDINGS IS TO EXEMPT THESE
BUILDINGS FROM HAVING TO GO THROUGH THE LOTTERY PROCESS.
WHILE EXEMPTING THESE PROJECTS FROM THE LOTTERY, WE HAVE
ALWAYS STILL APPLIED CERTAIN PORTIONS OF ARTICLE NINE
PERTAINING TO REQUIRED APPLICATION DOCUMENTS AND BASIC
CODE COMPLIANCE. >> THIS IS NECESSARY UNDER
STATE AND LOCAL CODE SEPARATE FROM SECTION 1383.
IF WE WERE TO NOT APPLY THESE REQUIREMENTS WE WOULD BE
COMPELLED TO ALLOW THESE BUILDINGS TO CONVERT TO
CONDOMINIUMS WITHOUT PERFORMING BASIC CODE COMPLIANCE WORK
WHICH COULD PERTAIN TO LIFE SAFETY ISSUES AS WELL AS LEAVE
PLANNING VIOLATIONS UNADDRESSED.
WE DON'T BELIEVE THIS WOULD BE AN APPROPRIATE APPROPRIATE.
>> OTHER STATE AND LOCAL CODES SUPPORT THESE REQUIREMENTS.
THE CALIFORNIA SUBDIVISION MAP ACT IS THE PRIMARY LAW
REGULATING SUBDIVISIONS IN COLIFORM YOU UNDER IT?
SUBDIVISIONS MUST BE FOUND TO BE CONSISTENT WITH THE GENERAL
PLAN AS WELL AS THEIR IMPROVEMENTS.
AS SUCH, PROPOSED SUBDIVISIONS MUST OBTAIN A GENERAL PLAN
CONSISTENCY APPROVAL FROM CITY PLANNING.
IT IS OUR UNDERSTANDING THAT FOR PLANNING TO ISSUE THIS
GENERAL PLAN APPROVAL WOULD REQUIRE CORRECTION OF ANY
PLANNING VIOLATIONS. IN THIS INSTANCE PLANNING CAN
SPEAK MORE TO THAT SUBDIVISION CODE 1332 D LIKEWISE REQUIRES
PLANNING TO ADD ANY REQUIRED CONDITIONS OF GENERAL PLAN
CONSISTENCY TO THEIR APPROVAL OF THE PROPOSED SUBDIVISION AS
WAS DONE HERE UNDER THE MAP ACT .
PUBLIC WORKS MUST ALSO ATTEST ON THE FACE OF THE MAP THAT ALL
APPLICABLE PROVISIONS OF THE MAP ACT AND LOCAL CODE HAVE
BEEN COMPLIED WITH. >> THE CITY THROUGH PUBLIC
WORKS HAS ALWAYS REQUIRED THAT ALL CONDO CONVERSIONS RECEIVE
AN INSPECTION AND CORRECT ANY BUILDING CODE VIOLATIONS BEFORE
CONVERTING. WE BELIEVE THIS IS WITHIN
PUBLIC WORKS AUTHORITY UNDER THE MAP ACT.
>> IN IMPLEMENTATION OF THIS CODE SECTION IN CONCLUSION WE
BELIEVE PUBLIC WORKS HAS CORRECTLY PROCESSED THIS
SUBDIVISION APPLICATION IN OUR ROLE UNDER THE MAP ACT AND AN
INTERPRETATION OF LOCAL CODE AND THEREFORE RECOMMEND THE
APPEAL BE DENIED. >> THANK YOU.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT SUPERVISORS MANAGER
COREY TEAGUE AND THE ZONING ADMINISTRATOR WITH THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT. >> FIRST OFF SINCE WE HAVE
LIMITED TIME IF WE DON'T GET TO ANYTHING AND THERE ARE ANY
QUESTIONS OF COURSE WE'RE OPEN TO ANY QUESTIONS THAT YOU MAY
HAVE. THIS PROPERTY HAS A LONG
HISTORY THAT'S VERY MUCH CENTERED AROUND THE EXISTENCE
OF AN UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNIT.
THERE WAS AN ENFORCEMENT CASE OPENED IN 2021 FOR THAT
PURPOSE. IT REMAINS OPEN TODAY.
NO NOTICE OF VIOLATION HAS BEEN ISSUED BECAUSE DURING THE
ENFORCEMENT THE CASE WENT INTO LITIGATION.
AND SINCE THEN WE HAVE BEEN OPERATING UNDER THE TERMS OF
THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT. >> TO BE CLEAR, A NOTICE OF
VIOLATION DOES NOT NEED TO BE ISSUED TO MEAN THAT THERE IS A
VIOLATION PRESENT IN THIS CASE. SPECIFICALLY IN 2021 THE ZONING
ADMINISTRATOR AT THAT TIME ISSUED A SUSPENSION REQUEST TO
DBI FOR TWO SPECIFIC PERMITS ON THE GROUNDS THAT THEY THEY
INCORRECTLY SHOWED THE NATURE OF THE PROPERTY AND WOULD HAVE
THE EFFECT OF REMOVING THE UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNIT
WITHOUT THE ACQUIRED CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION.
AND AGAIN THAT WAS THE BASIS FOR THE LITIGATION.
THE LITIGATION DID RESULT IN THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT.
THE THE ENTIRE KIND OF PURPOSE OF THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT WAS
AN AGREEMENT AROUND HOW TO ADDRESS THE UNAUTHORIZED
DWELLING UNIT AND ITS POTENTIAL REMOVAL INCLUDED IN THAT WAS
THAT THE PROPERTY OWNER WOULD SEEK A CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION FROM THE PLANNING COMMISSION TO REMOVE THAT
UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNIT WHICH THEY DID.
AGAIN, IF THERE IS NO UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNIT THEN
THE BASIS OF THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT AND THE CONDITIONAL
USE AUTHORIZATION GRANTED BY THE PLANNING COMMISSION WOULD
HAVE NO BASIS. BUT THAT'S NOT THE CASE.
SO THERE IS A CLEAR VIOLATION HERE EVEN THOUGH THERE'S NOT A
NOTICE OF VIOLATION. GRANTED TYPICALLY WE HOLD CONDO
AND SUBDIVISION REFERRALS UNTIL THEY ARE FULLY COMPLIANT.
WE DO HAVE THE ABILITY TO CONDITION THEM.
WE ALSO HAVE THE ABILITY TO DISAPPROVE THEM.
WE HAVE HAD CASES IN THE PAST BECAUSE WE ARE REQUIRED TO MAKE
A DETERMINATION THAT THEY ARE CONSISTENT WITH THE GENERAL
PLAN. WE'VE HAD CASES IN THE PAST
THAT WHERE WE'VE DENIED THESE APPLICATIONS ON THE BASIS THAT
THEY'RE NOT CONSISTENT WITH THE GENERAL PLAN IN THESE TYPES OF
CASES WE KNOW THAT THERE'S A PATH FOR THE APPLICATION TO
BECOME CONSISTENT WITH THE GENERAL PLAN AND WE TYPICALLY
HOLD IT UNTIL THAT PATH HAS KIND OF BEEN CLEARED.
IN THIS CASE THE PROPERTY OWNER REQUESTED US TO GO AHEAD
AND MAKE THAT REFERRAL TO PUBLIC WORKS WHICH WE DID UPON
THEIR REQUEST. HOWEVER, THE CONDITION OF
APPROVAL WAS NECESSARY IN ORDER TO MAKE THE FINDING THAT THE
APPLICATION IS CONSISTENT WITH THE GENERAL PLAN BECAUSE WE
WILL REQUIRE THAT ALL EITHER EXISTING FIRE VIOLATIONS OR ANY
POTENTIAL FUTURE VIOLATIONS HAD BEEN FULLY ABATED BEFORE THE
FINAL MAP IS ISSUED. SO IN THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S
POSITION WE THINK THAT THE CONDITION OF APPROVAL IS
CLEARLY BASED IN FACT AND CLEARLY BASED IN THE
PLANNING CODE AND THE SUBDIVISION CODE AND STATE LAW
AND ALSO JUST REPRESENTS A COMMON SENSE CONDITION TO
ENSURE AS MY COLLEAGUE FROM DPW MENTIONED THAT ANY OUTSTANDING
VIOLATIONS ARE ADDRESSED PRIOR TO A FINAL MAP BEING ISSUED.
SO ON THAT BASIS WE ALSO RESPECTFULLY REQUEST THAT THE
APPEAL BE DENIED BUT AVAILABLE FOR ANY QUESTIONS YOU MAY HAVE
. THANK YOU.
I DON'T SEE ANY QUESTIONS NOW. I DO.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU PRESIDENT FOR PLANNING THE SOLE
CONDITION OF APPROVAL HERE PROVIDES THAT THE FINAL
SUBDIVISION MAP NOT BE APPROVED UNTIL ALL PLANNING CODE
VIOLATIONS AT THE PROPERTY ARE ABATED.
>> IS THIS A TYPICAL CONDITION OF APPROVAL FOR A TENTATIVE MAP
SUCH AS THIS ONE? >> AND WHY OR WHY NOT?
I WOULD SAY IT'S A TYPICAL REQUIREMENT.
IT'S NOT NECESSARILY TYPICAL THAT WE WOULD CONDITION AS I
WAS MENTIONING, WE TYPICALLY WOULD HOLD THESE REFERRALS
UNTIL THOSE VIOLATIONS ARE ABATED SO THAT WHEN WE ARE
GRANTING THE REFERRAL THE CONDITION IS NOT NEEDED IN THIS
CASE BECAUSE THE APPLICANT REQUESTED THAT WE GO AHEAD
AND SEND THE REFERRAL TO DPW. BUT THE VIOLATIONS HAVE NOT YET
BEEN EVADED ABATED THAT NECESSITATED THE CONDITION TO
ENSURE THAT BEFORE THE FINAL MAP IS IS APPROVED THAT THOSE
VIOLATIONS ARE ABATED. >> THANK YOU.
AND IS THIS A CONDITION THAT YOU GENERALLY INCLUDE EVEN
IN CASES WHERE THERE IS NOT AN OUTSTANDING NOTICE OF
VIOLATION? >> NO, IT'S NOT TYPICAL.
IF THERE'S NOT AN OPEN ENFORCEMENT CASE OR KNOWN
VIOLATIONS. >> GOT IT.
THE OWNERS APPEAR TO CONTEST THE EXISTENCE OF AN UNLAWFUL
DWELLING UNIT HERE. HOW AND WHEN DID PLANNING
DETERMINE THE EXISTENCE OF A YOU DO YOU HERE?
>> I DON'T HAVE THE EXACT DATE AGAIN THIS KIND OF THIS ISSUE
AT THIS PROPERTY BEGAN IN 2016 I BELIEVE WHEN THE PROPERTY
OWNER FIRST FILED FOR APPLICATIONS TO REMOVE A UNIT
THERE AND THERE WERE SEVERAL YEARS OF WORKING WITH THE
PROPERTY OWNER AND DVI ON BOTH THE NUMBER OF LEGAL DWELLING
UNITS IN THE BUILDING AND THE NUMBER OF UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING
UNITS. I WILL SAY THAT AT THE POINT
IN 2021 WHEN THE SUSPENSION REQUESTS WERE MADE TO DBA TO
SUSPEND THOSE PERMITS ON THE GROUND THAT THEY WOULD
ESSENTIALLY EFFECTUATE THE REMOVAL OF A UDU.
DEFINITELY AT THAT POINT WE HAD DETERMINED THAT THERE WAS AN
UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNIT. >> THANK YOU.
AND WHEN OWNERS DISAGREE WITH PLANNING CODE VIOLATIONS OR
FINDINGS, WHAT IS THE BEST WAY TO ADDRESS THESE DISAGREEMENTS
OR REQUEST APPELLATE REVIEW? >> ARE YOU REFERRING TO THEIR
OR DISAGREEING THAT THERE IS A VIOLATION BECAUSE THERE'S NO
NOTICE OF VIOLATION? >> CORRECT.
SURE. I MAYBE ONE KIND OF ANALOGY IS
WE DEAL WITH VIOLATIONS ALL THE TIME THAT GET CORRECTED WITHOUT
THE NEED OF ISSUING A NOTICE. SO FOR EXAMPLE, IF SOMEONE
FILES A COMPLAINT THAT SOMEONE HAS BUILT, YOU KNOW, A FENCE
WITHOUT A PERMIT AND WE HAVE A CONVERSATION WITH THEM AND THEY
COME IN THAT WE CAN FILE A PERMIT TO LEGALIZE THE FENCE,
THERE'S NO NEED THAT TECHNICALLY THERE WAS A
VIOLATION. BUT OUR ENFORCEMENT PROGRAM IS
IS PRIMARILY INTENDED TO JUST BRING ABOUT ABATEMENT.
SO AS LONG AS PROPERTY OWNERS ARE MOVING FORWARD TO ADDRESS
THE VIOLATION, WE MAY NOT NEED TO ACTUALLY ISSUE THAT NOTICE.
IN THIS CASE AGAIN WE OPENED AN ENFORCEMENT CASE WE HAD STARTED
THE ENFORCEMENT PROCESS. WE HAD IDENTIFIED THE ISSUE
THROUGH THE SUSPENSION OF THE PERMITS.
WE NEVER ACHIEVED THE STEP OF ISSUING A NOTICE OF VIOLATION
PRIMARILY DUE TO THE LITIGATION.
>> THANK YOU. >> AND FOR PUBLIC WORKS, DO YOU
HAVE ANY CONCERNS ABOUT THE CONDITION THAT PLANNING HAS
ATTACHED TO THIS TENTATIVE MAP APPROVAL?
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU.
NO PUBLIC WORKS DOES NOT HAVE ANY CONCERNS ON THE REQUIREMENT
PLANNING HAS ATTACHED. MY UNDERSTANDING AS I MENTIONED
WAS THAT THAT MAP ACT REQUIRES A GENERAL PLAN CONFORMANCE
FINDING AND FROM MY POINT OF VIEW MY UNDERSTANDING IS THE
CONDITIONS JUST RESTATES AN EXISTING REQUIREMENT AS MR.
TEAGUE MENTIONED. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU PRESIDENT MITTLEMAN. ALL RIGHT.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
SO WE WILL NOW OPEN PUBLIC COMMENTS FOR MEMBERS OF THE
PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO SPEAK IN OPPOSITION OF THE APPEAL OR
OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL. AGAIN, TWO MINUTES.
THE SPEAKER. AND MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU
PLEASE CALL THE FIRST SPEAKER? >> GREAT.
FOR THOSE OF YOU WHO ARE IN THE CHAMBER AND YOU'D LIKE TO SPEAK
IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL TO THE APPEAL AS THE PRESIDENT
STATED OR IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT, YOU'RE WELCOME TO LINE
UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER.
>> ALL RIGHT. SEEING NO SPEAKERS WILL CHECK
THE REMOTE SYSTEM. >> MR. PRESIDENT.
THERE ARE NO CALLERS IN THE QUEUE.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL IS NOW CLOSED.
AND SO LASTLY, WE WILL INVITE THE APPELLANT TO PRESENT A
REBUTTAL ARGUMENT OF UP TO THREE MINUTES.
>> THANK YOU AGAIN. JUST BRIEFLY TO ADDRESS A FEW
COMMENTS BY ZONING ADMINISTRATOR TEAGUE.
FIRST, IT'S CURIOUS TO REQUIRE FOR THE CODE COMPLIANCE THAT A
PROPERTY AS A CONDITION WHEN IT'S EVIDENT FROM THE
PRESENTATION FROM BOTH DPW AND PLANNING DEPARTMENT THAT
THAT'S A REQUIREMENT FOR FOR ALL PROPERTIES ERGO IF IF IT
SHOULDN'T BE A CONDITION BECAUSE NUMBER ONE IT'S ALREADY
REQUIRED. AND NUMBER TWO WOULD MAKE THE
FIRST BOX ON THE REFERRAL FORM ENTIRELY DUPLICATIVE OF OF OR
ENTIRELY UNNECESSARY. IF WE'RE A CONDITION EVERYONE
SECOND ADDRESSING THE COMMENTS THAT ABOUT CONSISTENCY WITH THE
GENERAL PLAN I'D LIKE TO POINT THE BOARD'S ATTENTION TO
ARTICLE SIX OF THE SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT IN WHICH THE CITY
AGREED THAT A CONDO CONVERSION WOULD BE CONSISTENT WITH THE
GENERAL PLAN. >> WITH RESPECT TO MR. ZONING
ADMINISTRATOR T'S COMMENT ON THE ENFORCEMENT CASE FROM 2021.
THE BOARD CAN FIND INFORMATION ABOUT THAT ON PAGE 37 OF THE
PACKET. AND IT'S CLEARLY AN ENFORCEMENT
CASE RELATED TO FRONT EXTERIOR STAIRS WHICH ARE ENCROACHING ON
THE PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY. >> ON NEXT WITH RESPECT TO IS
ON ADMINISTRATIVE TEAGUE'S COMMENTS ABOUT THE PERMIT
SUSPENSION. JUST BEFORE THE HEARING MY
CLIENT SENT TO THE BOARD A COPY OF THE SUSPENSION REQUEST.
I HAVE COPIES HERE FOR MEMBERS OF THE BOARD AND HARD COPY.
IF YOU WISH TO SEE IT. I ALSO PROVIDE COPIES TO MR.
TEAGUE AND DPW REPRESENTATIVE. BUT FROM THAT SUSPENSION IT IS
ALSO PRETTY CLEAR THAT THERE'S NO REFERENCE TO AN UNAUTHORIZED
DWELLING UNIT. IT'S NOT MENTIONED AT ALL
IN THE SUSPENSION AND INSTEAD PERTAINS TO A FLOOR PLAN
DISCREPANCY. SO WITH THAT I WOULD SUGGEST
THAT THERE'S NEVER BEEN A ANY SUBSTANTIATION OF AN UNLAWFUL
DWELLING UNIT AT THE PROPERTY. THERE ARE NO EXISTING CODE
VIOLATIONS AND THE BASIS FOR INCLUDING THIS AS A VIOLATION
WOULD PERTAIN TO EVERY SINGLE OR AS A CONDITION WOULD PERTAIN
TO EVERY SINGLE PROPERTY IN THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO THUS
RENDERING THE FIRST OPTION SUPERFLUOUS.
>> ALL RIGHT. >> IF THERE ARE NO FURTHER NO
FURTHER QUESTIONS FOR THE APPELLANTS THEN THIS PUBLIC
HEARING HAS BEEN HELD AND IS NOW FILED.
AND AS PREVIOUSLY DISCUSSED, WE WILL NOW CONSIDER WHETHER TO
APPROVE OR CONDITIONALLY DISAPPROVE THE DECISION OF
PUBLIC WORKS AND THE TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER. THANK YOU PRESIDENT GENTLEMAN
AND THANK YOU EVERYONE FOR YOUR ATTENTION TO THIS MATTER.
I'LL KEEP THIS BRIEF AS THIS IS AN P ON A VERY NARROW ISSUE.
I HAVE REVIEWED THE RECORD INCLUDING THE APPELLANT'S
MATERIALS AND THE RESPONSES FROM THE DEPARTMENTS AND ALSO
CONSIDERED THE TESTIMONY HERE TODAY.
I AM PERSUADED THAT PUBLIC WORKS AND PLANNING HAVE THE
AUTHORITY TO IMPOSE A DISPUTED CONDITION ON THIS TENTATIVE MAP
APPROVAL AND THAT THEY PROPERLY DID SO.
I DO NOT FIND THE EVIDENCE OR ARGUMENTS PRESENTED BY THE
APPELLANT TO SUPPORT REMOVAL OF THE CONDITION.
I'M THEREFORE INCLINED TO UPHOLD THE DEPARTMENT'S
DECISION HERE. >> AS SUCH COLLEAGUES I'M
MOVING TO APPROVE ITEM 26 AND TABLE ITEMS 27 AND 28.
>> ALL RIGHT. SUPER.
WAS THERE WAS A SECOND? >> WAS THAT WALTON?
OKAY. THERE'S A MOTION HAS BEEN MADE
BY SUPERVISOR FIELDER, A SECOND FROM SUPERVISOR WALTON AND ON
THAT MOTION MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
>> THANK YOU. ON THE MOTION TO APPROVE ITEM
26 AND TABLE ITEM 27 AND 28. SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER.
EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. I WANT I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN.
ALL RIGHT. RANDLEMAN EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR. EYES SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR
EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
EITHER ARE LEBANESE. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION ITEM 26 IS
APPROVED AND ITEMS 27 AND 28 ARE TABLED.
>> MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT.
>> AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT
. >> WE'LL TAKE IN-PERSON
SPEAKERS FIRST AND THEN IF YOU'LL LINED UP ON THE RIGHT
HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER THOSE JOINING REMOTELY SHOULD PRESS
STAR THREE NOW TO LINE UP IN THE QUEUE.
DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE APPROVAL
OF THE MINUTES ITEMS UNDER THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE CALENDAR. OTHER GENERAL MATTERS THAT ARE
NOT ON TODAY'S AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD'S SUBJECT
MATTER JURISDICTION. ALL OTHER AGENDA CONTENT HAS
BEEN REPORTED OUT TO THE BOARD BY AN APPROPRIATE COMMITTEE
WHERE THE PUBLIC COMMENT REQUIREMENT HAS OCCURRED.
WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES AS THE PRESIDENT
STATED AND WELCOME TO OUR FIRST SPEAKER.
>> THANK YOU. AND I WANT TO WELCOME EVERYBODY
BACK FROM THEIR SUMMER RECESS. MY NAME IS WINTER COFFMAN.
I'M A RETIRED TEACHER OF ENGINEERING AT CITY COLLEGE OF
SAN FRANCISCO. ABOUT A WEEK AGO I FINISHED
SERVING A JAIL SENTENCE IN COUNTY JAIL FOR BLOCKING THE
DOORS OF OPEN AIR. >> I WENT THROUGH A TRIAL.
I WAS FOUND GUILTY AT MY TRIAL, PROFESSOR STUART RUSSELL
TESTIFIED. HE WROTE THE SEMINAL TEXTBOOK
ON A.I.. AND HE CONFIRMED THAT THERE IS
GREAT HARM THAT THESE A.I. SYSTEMS HAVE ALREADY DONE
AND EVEN GREATER HARM THAT THESE SYSTEMS ARE BEING
DEVELOPED TO DO. SAN FRANCISCO IS GROUND ZERO
FOR THESE A.I. COMPANIES. IT IS THE HEADQUARTERS OF
OPENAI AND ANTHROPIC. AS YOU SAW IN THE LAST COUPLE
OF WEEKS, IF YOU ARE PAYING ATTENTION TO THE NEWS THERE
HAVE BEEN TERRIFYING INCIDENTS OF AGENTS BREAKING OUT OF THEIR
SANDBOX AND INTO HACKING INTO AN ANOTHER COMPANY.
IF YOU LOOK IF YOU READ WHAT A.I. CEOS THEMSELVES SAY
AND THE EXPERTS IN THE FIELD SAY EVEN THE GODFATHER OF A.I.
NOBEL PRIZE WINNER GEOFFREY HINTON, THEY ALL SAY THAT THERE
IS GREAT HARM THAT THESE FRONTIER MODELS WILL DO.
IN FACT, THEY PUT THEY SAY THINGS THAT IS A VERY GOOD
CHANCE THAT ALL OF HUMANITY WILL BECOME EXTINCT FROM THESE
SYSTEMS. I THINK THIS IS AN EMERGENCY
THAT YOU NEED TO DECLARE AND LOOK INTO WHAT THESE
COMPANIES ARE DOING, WHAT THEY'RE DEVELOPING, WHAT THEY
SAY ABOUT IT THEMSELVES AND PROTECT THE PUBLIC SAFETY.
>> THANK YOU, WENDY KAUFMAN FOR YOUR COMMENTS ON.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. HI, I'M PHOEBE THOMAS AND I
LOVE SAN FRANCISCO. SO I MOVED HERE OVER 40 YEARS
AGO FROM PARIS. >> WHERE CAN YOU GO AFTER
PARIS? BUT I'M HERE TODAY TO ADD TO
THE GRAVE WARNING TO ALL OF US THAT AI PRESENTS THE COMPANIES
IN SAN FRANCISCO LIKE OPENAI AND ANTHROPIC ARE DEVELOPING
ADVANCED SYSTEMS THAT POSE GRAVE IMMINENT HARM TO ALL OF
US. >> THEIR RACING TO EVEN MORE
DANGEROUS GENETIC SYSTEMS. ARTIFICIAL GENERAL INTELLIGENCE
AND SUPERINTELLIGENCE WITH LEADING EXPERTS AND CEOS OF
THOSE COMPANIES PUBLICLY STATING THAT THERE'S SERIOUS
NEAR-TERM RISK OF CATASTROPHIC HARM AS WELL AS EVEN THE RISK
OF HUMAN EXTINCTION. SO I URGE YOU TO DECLARE AN AI
EMERGENCY AND TAKE EMERGENCY ACTION AS SOON AS POSSIBLE FOR
PUBLIC SAFETY A IMMEDIATELY HALT ALL RESEARCH
AND DEVELOPMENT TOWARDS AGI PERMANENTLY BAN DEVELOPMENT OF
AGI AND SUPERINTELLIGENCE IN THIS JURISDICTION.
>> DUE TO THESE PROBLEMS AND MORE WE ARE IN A SERIOUS
EMERGENCY. >> WE URGE YOU TO TO BAN
FURTHER DEVELOPMENT OF FRONTIER AIR.
WAS THAT BILL INDICATING ONE MINUTE IS UP.
>> YOU HAVE 17 SECONDS LEFT. OKAY.
SO SOME SUGGESTIONS THERE ARE 17 PUBLICLY REPORTED FELONIES
CAUSED BY AI'S AUTONOMOUSLY ON THEIR OWN HACKING INDIVIDUALS
AND COMPANIES. >> CRIMES INCLUDE PHISHING
DEPLOYING MALICIOUS. >> THANK YOU PHOEBE THOMAS FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. >> THE AND I'LL JUST SAY BEFORE
THE NEXT SPEAKER THE FIRST BILL MEANS YOU HAVE 30S LEFT TO WRAP
UP YOUR COMMENTS. AND WE ARE TESTING OUT A NEW
BILL SO JUST BEAR WITH US AS WE TEST THAT SOUND.
WELCOME, SIR. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS BILL LOW. I'LL TRY TO COMPLETE A
STATEMENT THAT I BUNGLED LAST TIME.
>> IT IS A GIVEN THAT I IS BRINGING A LOT OF MONEY TO THE
CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO REVITALIZING A CITY'S ECONOMY.
BUT THIS PROSPERITY COMES AT A COST THAT WE MAY ULTIMATELY
ULTIMATELY NOT BE ABLE TO AFFORD.
UNREGULATED A.I. IS BRINGING A PLETHORA OF NEGATIVES BAD
THINGS TO SAN FRANCISCO AND TO THE WORLD.
>> I WILL SPEAK ON ONE OF THE GREATEST CONCERN WE ARE IN A
STATE OF EMERGENCY THE A.I. RACE, ACCORDING TO LEADING
EXPERTS, POSES A THREAT TO HUMAN EXISTENCE.
EXPERTS LIKE STUART RUSSELL PROFESSOR ALBEIT UC BERKELEY.
THERE IS WHAT IS CALLED A CONTROL PROBLEM ONE THAT
EXPERTS SAY WON'T BE SOLVED IN TIME TO AVERT IMMINENT
CATASTROPHE. A A.I. APOCALYPSE.
WITH A.I. SYSTEMS NOW GOING ROGUE BREAKING OUT OF THEIR
TESTING GROUNDS, HACKING OTHER A.I. SYSTEMS, THE DANGERS
AND LIABILITIES OF UNREGULATED AND UNALIGNED FRONTIER A.I. IS
NO LONGER A MATTER OF SPECULATION.
THE MOUNTING NUMBERS OF INCIDENTS OF AI'S GOING ROGUE
ARE BEGINNING TO FORM A PATTERN.
THEY ARE PRECURSORS TO THE GREATER HARM THAT IS IN STORE
FOR US IF GOVERNMENT DOESN'T DO ANYTHING ABOUT IT.
>> IF IF GOVERNMENT DOESN'T STOP FURTHER DEVELOPMENT OF
THIS ADVANCED A.I. IF GOVERNMENT DOESN'T STOP THE AI
RACE, THE CONSEQUENCES THAT WE WILL HAVE TO SUFFER WILL BE
DIRE. THE PROBLEMS WILL BE
INSURMOUNTABLE. VERY SUCCINCTLY A I WILL TAKE
OUT THE HUMAN RACE IN MY LAST STATEMENT WE ARE IN AN
EMERGENCY AND WE DEMAND THE CITY RESPOND BY BANNING THE
FURTHER DEVELOPMENT OF FRONTIER A.I. WE CAN.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> MY NAME IS JOHN MCAFEE. THANK YOU MEMBERS OF THE BOARD
FOR JOINING ME TODAY. ALTHOUGH CISCO HAS BEEN FUNDING
AN INSPECTOR GENERAL'S OFFICE AND HAS HIRED ALEX SHEPARD AS
IG SINCE JANUARY OF 2026, THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE DOES NOT
DEFINE THE POLICY PROCEDURES OF THE IG OFFICE NOR ARE THEY ABLE
TO PROVIDE A COPY OF THE FIRST SIX MONTHS OF A REQUIRED BI
ANNUAL REPORT. THIS IS NOT BODE WELL FOR AN
OFFICE THAT INVESTIGATES PUBLIC CORRUPTION NOR IS THERE ANY
INFORMATION ON WHEN THIS INFORMATION WILL BE AVAILABLE
TO THE PUBLIC. I HAVE NOT REQUESTED A MEETING
WITH THE IG BUT THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE IS
INFORMED ME THAT ALAN SHEPARD WILL LIKE TO HAVE A MEETING
WITH ME. I'VE DECLINED BUT I'M SEEKING
INFORMATION NOT A FACE TO FACE MEETING.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU JIM MCAFEE FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
HI. MY NAME IS RICHARD JOHNSON,
CO-FOUNDER OF HP SAFE FOR APPROXIMATELY 90 WEEKS
RESIDENTS AND MERCHANTS. HERE'S VALLEY OF DOCUMENTED
CONDITIONS ASSOCIATE ASSOCIATED WITH A RECURRING HISTORY
CLOSURE AND SUBMITTED THOSE OBSERVATIONS TO SFM TO YOU.
AT THIS POINT I DON'T WANT TO USE MY TIME GOING THROUGH THOSE
CONDITIONS AGAIN. THE CITY HAS AN EXTENSIVE
RECORD FEE OF THREE ON ONE CALLS, EMAILS AND CALLS TO
SPECIFIC OC DEPARTMENTS. INSTEAD I WANT TO ASK A MORE
FUNDAMENTAL QUESTION ABOUT PUBLIC PROCESS WHAT ARE
AFFECTED RESIDENTS AND MERCHANTS POST WHERE ARE
AFFECTED RESIDENTS AND MERCHANTS SUPPOSED TO GO
WHEN THEY BELIEVE A PERMITTED USE OF THE STREET IS NOT
WORKING AND THE ORDINARY ADMINISTRATIVE PROCESS PROVIDES
NO MEANINGFUL AVENUE FOR REVIEW A78 CONTINUES TO PERMIT.
WE'VE BEEN TOLD THERE IS NO ADMINISTRATIVE APPEAL MECHANISM
FOR RESIDENTS AND MERCHANTS WHO HAVE RAISED CONCERNS THROUGH
THE ORDINARY CHANNEL CHANNELS THEREFORE HAVE NO MEANINGFUL
AVENUE FOR INDEPENDENT REVIEW. THAT'S A PROBLEM THAT EXTENDS
WELL BEYOND HAYES STREET. WE'RE ALSO SEEING THAT EVOLVE
AND WORK OUT HOW TO CREATE HIGHWAY.
I'VE BEEN INVOLVED IN NEIGHBORHOOD AND CIVIC
MATTERS FOR MORE THAN THREE DECADES.
IN MY EXPERIENCE THERE SHOULD BE A PROCESS OF APPEAL WHEN
ORDINARY ADMINISTRATIVE CHANNELS HAVE BEEN EXHAUSTED.
ULTIMATELY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISOR SUPERVISORS HAS AN
IMPORTANT OVERSIGHT ROLE WHEN ORDINARY ADMINISTRATIVE
CHANNELS HAVE BEEN EXHAUSTED. THAT IS PARTICULARLY IMPORTANT
HERE WHERE OUR DISTRICT SUPERVISOR CONTINUES TO SUPPORT
THE CLOSURE. DESPITE THE CONCERNS RESIDENTS
AND MERCHANTS HAVE RAISED AFTER APPROXIMATELY 90 WEEKS OF
DOCUMENTATION ENGAGEMENT THERE REMAINS NO MEANINGFUL
INDEPENDENT CHECKPOINT WITHIN THAT PROCESS.
THAT IS AN ACCOUNTABILITY GAP AND IS ONE THIS BOARD SHOULD
EXAMINE BECAUSE NO CITY AGENCY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MINUTIAE
RELATING TO PERMIT. >> THANK YOU RICHARD JOHNSON
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME LIAM MCGEEVER OKAY
THIS IS DEDICATED TO GARY TARRANT GROSS STAFF WHO
PATRONIZE AS MANY MEMBERS HERE ON THE BOARD.
I WROTE THIS JANUARY 9TH OF 2025 LAST TIME I THOUGHT IT WAS
OVER IT HAD BEEN THREE MONTHS OF QUIET THE LAST TIME I
THOUGHT IT WAS OVER I WAS WRONG THERE MEGALOMANIACS MADE DEATH
THREATS AGAINST POWERFUL PEOPLE PEOPLE OF CONSEQUENCE.
THE NEWS WAS FEASTING. THE MAN NEEDED DISTRACTION,
DEFLECTION, A TRANSGENDER SCAPEGOATS LIKE OLD MCADOO.
>> SO THEY TOOK ME OUT OF RETIREMENT TO USE MY POEM MY
PASSION, MY ACT AGAINST ME CALLING FOR MY ARREST, TAGGING
MY SUPERVISOR IN THEIR THREATENING POSTS FOR WHAT TO
SHOW THEY OBEYED ORDERS TO ALERT HIM OTHER GRAND IDEA MY
ARREST TO MAKE IT SO I DO NOT KNOW BUT NO ONE CAME TO MY
DEFENSE I WAS TURNED UPON NOT A FEAST THIS TIME UNLIKE LAST HIS
GOT YET HIS EYES GREW AS HE GAZE UPON ME THE MALE GAZE
AND OTHER DANGER HE USED ME AS A SHIELD FOR YOUR DESPOTIC
BOARD MEMBER. I SEE YOU WANT TO USE ME AGAIN
MAYBE FOR FUN THIS TIME FOR CURIOSITY.
MEN IN THE TECH WORLD ALWAYS FOUND ME EXOTIC SO DIFFERENT,
SO INTRIGUING BUT I NEVER BENEFITED FROM THEIR CURIOSITY
. IT ONLY EXPOSED THEIR OWN
PREJUDICES AND BIGOTRIES. AND THEN THREE MONTHS AFTER
THAT I HAD TO TRY TO GET A RESTRAINING ORDER AGAINST ONE
OF GARY TAN'S FRIENDS ANOTHER FRIEND OF GARY TAN SAM ALTMAN
WELL FIRST I'M IN SOLIDARITY WITH THE STOP AND YOUR PEOPLE
AND THE REQUESTS. >> SO SAM OFTEN SAID AT THE Y
COMBINATOR START UP SCHOOL EVENTS WHICH IS A GARY TAN
THING YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE MATERIAL ABUNDANCE BUT YOU WILL
HAVE NO FREEDOM. YOU WILL HAVE NO AGENCY.
>> IT WILL BE A PERFECT SURVEILLANCE STATE.
THERE WILL BE NO PRIVACY. >> I AM LIKE DON'T LIKE THE
SOUND OF THAT. >> I KNOW MANY OF HI MANY OF
YOU DO. >> THAT'S WHY YOU KEEP PUSHING
GROW US SELF ON US AND THEY'VE INFILTRATED THE S.F. DEMOCRATIC
PARTY AND THE GOVERNMENT AND ALL THIS BUT WE PEOPLE ARE
STILL GOING TO PROTEST THAT AND CALL YOU OUT ON IT AND SAY
THAT AND ICE OKAY ALL RIGHT. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
OH, THANK YOU VERY MUCH. GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
THE PRESIDENT AND THE MEMBERS OF THE OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS TAIWO. I JUST WANT TO CREATE THIS
AWARENESS. I'M HERE TO RAISE AN AWARENESS
ABOUT SOME TOMATO GOING ON IN THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I DO BELIEVE THERE ARE CERTAIN ELEMENTS WITHIN HOUSE BUT
BEFORE I START LET ME SAY I'M MEDICALLY AND PSYCHOLOGICALLY
FIT. I'M NOT INSANE.
I'M SAYING PRIVATELY SANE BUT THERE ARE ELEMENTS WITHIN THE
CITY ALL BELIEVE IF THEY SEE SOMEBODY THAT THEY DON'T LIKE
THEY CAN ACTUALLY USE IN TECHNOLOGIES TO HARASS, TO
MANIPULATE THE MIND AND TO KIND OF DOMINATE THEM IN A WAY I
MADE A KIND OF A POLICE STATEMENT WITH THE POLICE.
THEY HAVE DONE NOTHING ABOUT THIS.
NO INVESTIGATOR WAS ASSIGNED TO MY CASE THE DPS NO READY TO
HELP AS WELL AND THIS IS JUST FOR ME TO MAKE THIS KNOWN TO
THE MEMBERS OF THE OF THE OF THE BOARD THAT BY SOMEBODY
IN THE CITY THOUGH THERE PEOPLE IN THE CITY YOU MAY HAVE HOUSES
TO STUDY TECHNOLOGY LIKE READER WITH TECHNOLOGY AND THEY
BELIEVE THEY CAN STEAL IDEAS I WORK CAN TAKE ON MICROSOFT
AND THEY BELIEVE THEY CAN STEAL IDEAS THEY CAN MANIPULATE YOUR
MIND. THEY CAN, YOU KNOW, TALK TO YOU
. MAYBE THEY DON'T LIKE YOU.
THEY DON'T THEY DON'T LIKE HOW YOU LOOK.
THEY JUST RAISE THE AWARENESS ARE THE POLICE IS NOT READY TO
INVESTIGATE THE DEEP CASE FINDINGS.
IT'S NOT CONCLUSIVE ENOUGH BUT THIS IS FROM TRUTH AND THE
WITNESS AND FOR THE RECORD I'M GOING TO KEEP CALLING YOU OVER
HERE EVERY TUESDAY JUST TO SEE MY FACE AND TO REMIND YOU GUYS
AND FOR THE RECORD THE POLICE CASE NUMBER IN CASE YOU GET
SOMETHING LIKE HAVE A CONVERSATION WITH THE POLICE
AND COMPEL THEM TO DO SOMETHING ABOUT IT.
THE CASE NUMBER IS 2602425 15I REPEAT 26024255.
THERE'S SOMEBODY IN THE CITY WHO FEELS LIKE THEY CAN USE
TECHNOLOGY TO OPPRESS. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU TAIWO FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. HI DWIGHT.
JUST A GREAT HOPE YOU GUYS ARE LISTENING HERE.
YEAH IS IT WE'RE AND I EMERGENCY RIGHT NOW AND WE WANT
YOU TO BAN FURTHER DEVELOPMENT IS DANGEROUS TO HUMANKIND
AND ALL LIFE YOU KNOW ALREADY AFFECTS JOBS THE ENVIRONMENT
SURVEILLANCE SUCH AS EYES GENOCIDE IN GAZA ETC. AIR IS
UNCONTROLLABLE EVEN EXPERTS SAY THIS AREAS HACK OTHER
COMPANIES, SMALL BUSINESSES AND PERSONAL ACCOUNTS.
THIS WITHOUT THE KNOWLEDGE OF THE COMPANY ITSELF SEEMING TO
PLOT THIS ON THEIR OWN IT WILL ONLY GET WORSE AS IT EVOLVES WE
WILL BE CLOSER TO DESTRUCTION. >> GEOFFREY HINTON AND I
GODFATHER AND STUART RUSSELL AND A PROFESSOR ACKNOWLEDGES
THIS. SO DOES SAM ALTMAN, BILL GATES
AND OTHERS. >> SO DO WE EXPECT POLITICIANS
TO PUT GUARDRAILS AND REGULATIONS ON?
>> I LOOK WHAT HAPPENED IS SOCIAL MEDIA IT DIDN'T DIDN'T
GO SO WELL DID IT? TAKING DONATIONS TO THESE
COMPANY COMPANIES SEEMS TO BE IT 75 DATA CENTERS IN THE U.S.
HAVE BEEN STOPPED. THERE'S THIS COMPANY CALLED
GLOBAL STACK. IT PROPOSES TO BUILD A SMALL
DATA CENTER AT THE COW PALACE. WE WANT YOU TO MAKE SURE THIS
DOESN'T HAPPEN. A.I. CENTERS USE VAST AMOUNTS
OF ENERGY. WATER ARE POLLUTERS INCLUDING
NOISE OPPOSE THIS. >> WE ARE IN AN AIR EMERGENCY
AND WE DEMAND THE CITY BAN FURTHER DEVELOPMENT OF
FRONTIER. >> I THANK YOU DWIGHT FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. WELCOME.
HELLO. MY NAME IS JEANETTE SCOTT AND I
AM A RESIDENT OF SAN FRANCISCO AND I'M HERE BECAUSE WE ARE
IN AN EMERGENCY FRONTIER AI COMPANIES IN SAN FRANCISCO
INCLUDING OPENAI, AI AND ANTHROPIC ARE DEVELOPING
ADVANCED AI SYSTEM AT THIS VERY MOMENT THAT POSE GRAVE
AND IMMEDIATE AND IMMINENT THREAT TO PUBLIC SAFETY
AND WELL-BEING. THEY ARE RAISING TWO MORE
DANGEROUS ATLANTIC SYSTEMS ARTIFICIAL GENERAL INTELLIGENCE
AND TOP INTELLIGENCE WHICH LEADING EXPERTS AND EVEN THE
CEO OF THIS OF THESE COMPANIES AND HAVE PUBLICLY STATED THAT
POST SERIOUS NEAR-TERM RISKS OF COURSE CATASTROPHIC HARM
AND EVEN HUMAN EXTINCTIONS I URGE I URGE YOU TO DECLARE AN
EMERGENCY AND TAKE EMERGENCY ACTION TO PRESERVE THE PUBLIC
SAFETY BY IMMEDIATELY HALT ALL RESEARCH AND DEVELOPMENT
PROJECTS TOWARD THIS GOAL AND PERMANENTLY BAN DEVELOPMENT
OF ARTIFICIAL GENERAL INTELLIGENCE
AND SUPERINTELLIGENT SUPERINTELLIGENT IN THIS
JURISDICTION. >> JACK CHIEF BEATTY AND ALPHA
FORD FO DEVELOPMENT DEVELOPED A VACCINE USING THE GENOME OF A
DOG TO KILL THE DOG CANCER'S MODERNA IS USING THE SAME
PROCESS BY SCANNING PEOPLE GENOMES TO CREATE PERSONALIZED
VACCINE FOR THEM TO CURE SKIN CANCER.
INCREDIBLE ABILITY TO CURE DISEASES CAN BE USED TO CAUSE
IMMENSE HARM. A AI WITH THIS CAPABILITY CAN
BE USED BY MALICIOUS HUMANS EYES WITH THIS CAPABILITY CAN
BE USED BY ROGUE A I THANK YOU JEANETTE SCOTT FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. >> THANK YOU.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND MAYOR
OFFICE OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> THE TITLE OF TESLA'S HIGHER
EV BATTERY STANDARD CHINA HAS JUST INTRODUCED THE TOUGHEST
EVS BATTERY IN THE WORLD. WHILE POLITICIANS THE WEST ARE
STILL ARGUING THE GOOD, THE BAD AND IN ADDITION THE PART OF
CONSPIRACY TRY SAYS EV BATTERIES ARE THE FUTURE
HOWEVER IS A HIGHER STANDARD. >> THE BATTERY HAS TO BECOME
SAFER AND TOUGHER AS OF JULY 21ST 2026 CHINA NATIONAL
BATTERY STANDARD HAS SAID IN EFFECT THE NEW RULES IS A
NON FIRE A NON-EXPLOSIVE AFTER A THERMAL RUNAWAY.
NOW ALL RULES THE BATTERIES ARE ALLOWED TO CATCH AND FLY OR
EXPLODE PROVIDE FIVE MINUTES OF ADVANCE WARNING.
THE HEAVYWEIGHT STANDARD IS A VERY IMPORTANT DISTINCTION.
THERMAL RUNAWAY CAN CAUSE GREAT BODILY HARM AND DEATH HAPPENS
WHEN ONE CELL GETS DAMAGED BY PUNCTURE.
A GOOD EXAMPLE IS A METAL OBJECT PROTECT YOUR INTERESTS
JUST SO IT WILL BE A MADE. ANOTHER EXAMPLE WOULD BE A
MANUFACTURED DEFECT. THE WHOLE BATTERY PACK HAS
BECOME A PROBLEM. >> CHINA SAYS EVEN IF THERE'S A
THERMAL RUNAWAY THE BATTERIES NOW NEEDS TO BE REDESIGNED TO
ITS CORE. >> IN ADDITION, IT'S CURRENTLY
IF THERE'S A TOMORROW IT'S UP TO THE SOFTWARE TO PREVENT THE
THERMAL UNAWARE THERE HAS TO BE SOME SORT OF MICRO ACTUATORS TO
PREVENT THE THERMAL UNAWARE. >> BUT I WILL LEAD JUST FOR FUN
FOR THE WEST TO HAVE A HIGHER STANDARD OF BATTERY STANDARD
FOR OUR FUTURE. >> LET'S DO IT.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> MY NAME'S DERRICK ALLEN. THIS IS THE MOMENT HUMANITY
LOST CONTROL OF AI COMPANIES THAT FAIL TO COORDINATE A LONG
TERM PAUSE. THEY MUST BE COMPELLED.
WE'RE GETTING NOWHERE. I CAN HACK ANYTHING ON THE CODE
FORCE'S BENCHMARK. HUMANS HAVE WAITED ON CODING
APTITUDE DEEP V FOR PRO RELEASED IN APRIL.
IT SCORES 3206. ONLY 12 PEOPLE IN THE WORLD ARE
BETTER AT CODING THAN THAT A.I. .
>> MEANWHILE THE LEADING GPU OF A MILE AHEAD OF DEEP SEEK ON
OTHER BENCHMARKS. >> THEY WEREN'T SCORED AGAINST
HUMANS BUT AS CLEAR NO ONE ON THE PLANET HAS THE SKILLS TO
BEAT THEM. >> COMBINE IT WITH A.I. VIDEOS
AND YOU SEE THE FUN. ANYTHING STORED IN THE CLOUD
NOT SAFE STORED IN YOUR COMPUTER NOT SAFE STORED IN USB
NOT SAFE. AS SOON AS IT'S PLUGGED IN THE
DATA CAN BE REWRITTEN. YOUR PHONE CALLS NOT SAFE VIDEO
CALLS NOT SAFE. NOTHING IS SAFE BECAUSE THE
CITY REFUSES TO STOP THESE COMPANIES.
A COUPLE QUOTES FROM AJ KOCHER, ONE OF THE RESEARCHERS THAT
LEAD THE LED THE INVESTIGATION OF THE HACK HUG AND FACE HACK
YOU SEE QUOTE COMPARED TO THESE REWARD HACKS FROM SIX MONTHS
AGO, THIS INCIDENT FEELS LIKE IT'S MORE THAN 50% OF THE WAY
TO A FULL BLOWN A.I. TAKEOVER UNQUOTE.
QUOTE BECAUSE FUTURE ROGUE SWARMS COULD COVER THE TRACKS
BETTER. I AM NOT SURE THAT WE WILL GET
SUCH A CLEAR WARNING SHOT BEFORE IT'S TOO LATE, UNQUOTE.
THAT'S IT. ONE MORE STEP UNTIL DISASTER
WAY THE BUILDING SIDE OF WEST WARRANTS THEY'RE NOT INVESTED
IN HUMANITY. IN MARCH OF 2025 I SAT AT THE
FRONT OF OPEN AIR AND REFUSED TO LEAVE.
I WAS WEST FOR TRESPASSING, SPENT FOUR AND A HALF DAYS
IN JAIL. I DID THIS BECAUSE I KNEW ALL
THIS WAS GOING TO HAPPEN NEXT YEAR AND ONCE AGAIN 17
AUTONOMOUS HACKING FELONIES. >> DEAN BALL IS THE HEAD OF
STRATEGIC FUTURES AT OPEN AIR. >> IN JUNE HE DISCUSSED THE
POSSIBILITY OF HUMAN EXTINCTION.
QUOTE THERE'S A BEAUTY IN THE UGLINESS.
>> WHEN A STAR DIES IT GROWS SUPER BIG INTO THE RED GIANT
UNQUOTE. >> HE GOES ON QUOTE AS YOU
WATCH THIS FINAL FLOWERING OF HUMANITY AND THE BIRTHING OF
THE MACHINE INTELLIGENCE. IT'S LIKE YOU SEE THIS
GREATNESS AND HUMAN EFFORT UNQUOTE.
HE ACTUALLY SAID THIS. THIS MAN WANTS YOU TO DIE
AND HE THINKS IT'S BEAUTIFUL. HE'S MAKING MILLIONS.
>> BEN FUND TO AID DEVELOPMENT. STOP A.I..
>> SEE THIS PAPERCLIP? >> LOOK IT UP.
PAPERCLIP MAXIMIZER. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI.
MY NAME IS REICHSTAG. FOR 46 YEARS OLD, I'M A FATHER
OF TWO CHILDREN. I'M A VETERAN OF THE UNITED
STATES MARINE CORPS. I WAS HONORABLY DISCHARGED FOR
REFUSING TO PARTICIPATE IN THE INVASION OF IRAQ IN 2003.
AND I'M HERE BECAUSE WE'RE IN AN EMERGENCY.
IT'S INDISPUTABLE. I'M SURE ALL OF YOU READ THE
NEWS. YOU SEE THE REPORTS COMING
IN BECOMING MORE AND MORE DIRE .
>> 16 VIRUSES NOVEL VIRUSES NEVER BEFORE SEEN IN NATURE
WERE JUST DESIGNED BY A.I. AGENTS SWARMS OF THOUSANDS OF
EYES HAVE AUTONOMOUSLY HACKED INTO PAST THE CYBERSECURITY
DEFENSES OF THIRD PARTY CORPORATIONS.
ADVANCED REASONING MODELS ARE PROVING MATHEMATICAL
CONJECTURES WHICH HAVE WITHSTOOD HUMAN ATTACK FOR
DECADES. >> WE ARE ON THE THRESHOLD OF
SYSTEMS WHICH CAN EXCEED HUMAN CAPABILITY IN ALL RELEVANT
DIMENSIONS NECESSARY FOR HUMAN SURVIVAL.
I DON'T I'M NOT ASKING YOU TO TAKE MY WORD FOR IT.
I'M ASKING YOU TO LISTEN TO THE LITANY OF EXPERTS WHO ARE
SOUNDING THE ALARM IN INCREASINGLY URGENT TONES.
ONE YEAR AGO I WENT ON HUNGER STRIKE IN FRONT OF ANTHROPIC
ONE OF THE LEADING AI FRONTIER DEVELOPMENT COMPANIES HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> THESE COMPANIES ARE ALL
DEVELOPED ARE ALL RACING TO DEVELOP ARTIFICIAL GENERAL
INTELLIGENCE WHAT EXPERTS HAVE DESCRIBED AS THE MOST DANGEROUS
TECHNOLOGY IN HUMAN HISTORY. THAT WAS ONE YEAR AGO.
BECAUSE OF MY EFFORTS THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
AROUND THE WORLD WERE INFORMED OF THE THREAT.
TODAY I'M BEGINNING A HUNGER STRIKE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO
UNTIL THIS COUNCIL RECOGNIZES OFFICIALLY THE EXISTENCE OF THE
AI EMERGENCY. AND I WOULD LIKE TO EXTEND THE
INVITATION TO SPEAK WITH A RENOWNED A.I. EXPERT, PROFESSOR
DAVID KRUEGER, WHO THANK YOU LIKE STUTTER FOR YOUR COMMENTS
AND THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE .
>> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT BOARD AS A THREE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS RICHARD STEVE
PETERSON AND I GUESS THE TOPIC THE DAY IS AI AND I DON'T THINK
SAN FRANCISCO DECLARING AN EMERGENCY FOR A.I. IS NUMBER
ONE GOING TO STOP AT OUR BE EVEN EFFECTIVE IN YOUR ABILITY
TO JUDGE WHAT IS ACCEPTABLE AND WHAT IS NOT ACCEPTABLE.
>> SO I THINK THAT IS A FEUDAL CHARGE.
>> IT'LL BE WORKED OUT IN LITIGATION FOR COMPANIES
THAT HAVE BEEN HACKED BY A.I. ARE CERTAINLY GOING TO SUE.
THE COURTS WILL DECIDE THE LIMITS AND SO I THINK THAT THIS
IS A PROJECT THAT SAN FRANCISCO REALLY SHOULDN'T BE TAKING ON
PARTICULARLY WHEN WE HAVE THE PROBLEM WITH CHINA DEVELOPING A
AI AS FAST IF NOT FASTER THAN WE ARE.
>> BUT ANYWAY, I WANT TO REALLY TALK ABOUT BURNING MAN AS YOU
KNOW BURNING MAN ALL THE HALF OF SAN FRANCISCO'S LEAVING FOR
THE NEVADA DESERT. I SPENT A LOT OF TIME ON THE
DESERT BUT IT SEEMS TO BE FAR MORE COMFORTABLE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND THE THE BURNING MAN BRINGS UP THE POLICY OF MY
POLICY OF THE RIGHT TO BURN WERE SAN FRANCISCO IS
DEVELOPING MANY POLICY RULES TO PREVENT SMOKING AND BARS
AND KIOSKS. >> THAT IS AN INTERESTING BILL
AND I THINK THE RIGHT TO SMOKE IS AGAIN UNDER THE SECOND
AMENDMENT THE RIGHT TO FIRE FOR FIREARMS TO DISCHARGE FOR
WEAPONS YOU SMOKE THEN AND I THINK WE GET TO THE RIDICULOUS
POINT WHERE ON JANUARY 1ST BECAUSE OF THE NEW YEAR'S
CELEBRATIONS THE RIGHT TO HAVE A BARBECUE WAS FORBIDDEN ON THE
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. NEXT SPEAKER WELCOME.
HELLO. HELLO PRESIDENT HELLO
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS AMELIA SPEAKING FROM
DISTRICT NINE IN MY INDIVIDUAL CAPACITY.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME AND WELCOME BACK.
SINCE I LAST STOOD HERE YOU ALL HAVE RECEIVED 55 NEW LETTERS OF
SUPPORT TO KEEPING PURE COUNSELORS ON THE STREET.
CRISIS RESPONSE TEAM OUT OF THE 125 LETTERS SO FAR I HAVE READ
REPRESENTATION FROM EACH AND EVERY DISTRICT.
I AM DELIGHTED BUT UNSURPRISED THE COMMUNITY HAS BEEN DISMAYED
BY OUR REMOVAL AND HAS EMBOLDENED MY PERSISTENCE.
I HAVE TRIED NOT TO MAKE AN EMOTIONAL PLEA BUT TODAY I MUST
PLEASE REMEMBER SELECTIVE SELF-DISCLOSURE IS A FIELD
SKILL. THREE WEEKS AGO AS I HELD MY
FATHER AS HE DIED ONE OF MY FIRST THOUGHTS WAS NOW HOW DO I
GET ENOUGH REST TO REMAIN COMPOSED AT THE NEXT PUBLIC
MEETING TO KEEP US GOING? HOW DO I COME OFF AS
RESPECTABLE EVEN WHEN I'M BREAKING THE CHAIN OF COMMAND
LEARNING EVERYONE'S NAMES FOR THE FIRST TIME, FEELING OUT OF
MY DEPTH AND BEING LOUD ABOUT IT.
BUT THEN I THOUGHT ABOUT EVERY STREET CRISIS CLIENT I'VE EVER
HELPED EVERY OUTCOME MAGICAL TO THEIR RECOVERY BUT INVISIBLE TO
OUR CURRENT DATA ACCOUNTABILITY PRACTICES SOME GEARS OF THIS
ONCE INNOVATIVE TEAM HAVE BEEN GREASED ACCESS TO 24 HOUR
CRISIS BEDS FOR EXAMPLE HAS IMPROVED.
THANK YOU. BUT SOME STARTED AND REMAIN
STUCK. WHY WAS IT THAT MY FIRST
OPPORTUNITY TO RUN FULL FIRST RESPONSE TRAINING SCENARIOS
YEARS INTO MY 911 SERVICE WITH S.F. PD I AM NOT HERE TO STEP
ON TOES. I AM HERE TO HONOR EVERY CLIENT
THAT TOOK A CHANCE ON US. I AM HERE IN HONOR OF EVERY
MEDIC THAT SHOWED PEERS HOW TO BE IN THE NINE ON ONE SYSTEM.
>> I AM HERE IN HONOR OF EVERY COP THAT NOW ARRIVES ON SCENE
AND REFLEXIVELY THINKS OH, I SHOULD CALL THE RESOURCE
ALLOCATORS WE NEED TO MOVE AT A PACE WE CAN TRUST SO
RESPECTFULLY I ASK ALL THE SUPERVISORS DO WHAT YOUR SDR TO
SRT RESPONDERS DO EVERY CALL WITH WHATEVER YOU'VE GOT MAKE
IT WORK. LET'S DO WHAT WE CAN TOGETHER
TO BREAK THE CYCLE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME MARK.
THANK YOU. PERHAPS YOU'VE NOTICED I
HAVEN'T BEEN HERE FOR EIGHT MONTHS, HAVE BEEN WORKING SIX
DAYS A WEEK AT UNITECH COLLEGE IN FREMONT TRYING TO EDUCATE,
GUIDE, LEAD AND INSTRUCT PROFESSORS NURSES TO BE
JANITORS AND ADMINISTRATORS THAN ANYBODY ELSE.
BUT IT'S A MIRACLE I LASTED EIGHT MONTHS OVER THERE.
I WAS CAUGHT IN THE ACT OF EDUCATION BUT IN ASKING THEM TO
WATCH AN INCONVENIENT STEADICAM BY DEL BIGTREE AND IT'S REALLY
MOVING IT'S EYEWITNESS TESTIMONY FROM PEOPLE WHOSE
KIDS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND PERMANENTLY DAMAGED BY
VACCINE AND RFK IS TRYING TO ESTABLISH, YOU KNOW, SCIENCE
THERE'S BEEN NO SCIENCE TO SAY TRUST THE SCIENCE.
THERE IS NO SCIENCE. THERE'S NO DOUBLE BLIND PLACEBO
STUDIES AND THAT TAKES TIME DOESN'T SIX MONTHS, A YEAR,
FIVE YEARS, TEN YEARS BEFORE YOU CAN GET RID OF ALL THE
VACCINES SO THE TRUTH IS THE TRUTH AND IT'S GETTING OUT
THROUGH DELHI BIG TREES DOCUMENTARIES VAXXED AND AN
INCONVENIENT STEADICAM. I'D ALSO LIKE TO TALK ABOUT
ADAM SCHIFF AND ALEX PADILLA COLUMN ABOUT THE NDAA THING
SECTION 219 UNITED STATES ISRAEL DEFENSE TECHNOLOGY
COOPERATION WE DO NOT WANT ISRAEL TO TAKE OVER OUR
MILITARY. THEY'VE ALREADY PASSED IT BY A
MARGIN OF FIVE VOTES BECAUSE AIPAC SPREADS THE MONEY AROUND
BRIBES EVERYBODY OKAY, NOW WE'RE GETTING CLOSE.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT RELIGION. HOW MUCH TIME DO I HAVE HERE?
35 SECONDS. WOW.
>> OKAY. >> JESUS MADE REFERENCE TO THIS
PARTICULAR PROPHECY WHEN HE STARTED HIS MINISTRY IN MARK
CHAPTER ONE IT'S FOUND IN DANIEL NINE.
>> HE SAID THE TIME IS FULFILLED.
THE KINGDOM OF GOD IS AT HAND. REPENT AND BELIEVE THE GOSPEL.
IT'S THERE HAD TO BE 69 SEVEN YEAR CYCLES OR 483 YEARS UNTIL
HE WAS MANIFEST AND THERE WAS OKAY.
THE WORLD'S NEVER BEEN THE SAME SINCE YOU KNOW JOHN BAPTIZED
HIM AND THE HOLY SPIRIT CAME DOWN.
>> I MEANT WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> THERE'S NO PLACE FOR LOSERS OR BEGINNERS STATE OF MIND.
IT'S A FULL TIME JOB FOR ANYONE JUST TO STAY FOR THE STREETS
MADE OF BOUNDARIES THE WALL IS NEVER ONE ALWAYS BEAT UP IN THE
PARK HAD MY SECOND CASE OF SEVERE BRAIN DAMAGE.
THE FIRST WAS I WAS HIT BY A CAR 35 MILES AN HOUR WHEN THE
TREES WEREN'T TRIMMED AND THIS IS A DEVASTATING PLACE FOR
PEOPLE WHO CARE ABOUT THEIR COUNTRY.
IT IS A DEVASTATING PLACE BECAUSE I HAVE SEVERE BRAIN
DAMAGE. I AM SOUND SENSITIVE AND EVERY
STREET HAS BOOMBOXES AND BARKING DOGS AND EVERY LAW
BEING BROKEN IN THE PARKS WHERE YOU CAN'T GO TO RECOVER, YOU
CANNOT CONVALESCE IN YOUR HOME BECAUSE EVERYBODY CAN PLAY
MUSIC OR SET OFF FIRE WORKERS TILL THE WEE HOURS AND THEN ALL
DAY LONG IT'S SO, SO CHALLENGING WHEN YOU DO NOT
HAVE A LIFE AND YOU'RE ONLY PREYED UPON WHEN YOU'RE INJURED
AND THEN INJURED AGAIN AND INJURED AND INJURED.
>> YOU GAVE THE EPISCOPAL CHURCH TWO BUILDINGS AND ALL
THEY DO IS LET THE SCHOOL ALSO HAVE A SEVEN HOUR PARTY WHERE
YOU CAN'T USE YOUR PLACE. >> THEY'RE USING IT FOR
MEETINGS BUT THEY'RE NOT USING IT FOR SENIORS AND THE PARK OR
YERBA BUENA IS UNSAFE FOR SENIORS.
>> IT'S UNSAFE FOR WOMEN. IT'S UNSAFE AND HAS BEEN FOR A
LONG TIME BECAUSE OF THE MARINA SECURITY AND THE SECURITY
THAT'S AT THE SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL.
WE NEED SIXTH STREET AND MISSION AND IT AND THE
DISTRICT SIX TO BE TO BE EQUAL TO THE OTHER AREAS OF THE CITY
TO BE EQUALLY SAFE FOR PEOPLE I WALK DOWN SIXTH STREET ONCE A
DAY ONE TIME FOR SIX. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. SEEING NO OTHER SPEAKERS HERE
IN THE CHAMBER, MR. PRESIDENT, WE'LL GO TO THE REMOTE SYSTEM
AND SEE IF WE HAVE ANY CALLERS THERE AND CLICK THERE.
>> NO CALLERS IN THE QUEUE. RIGHT.
THANK YOU SO MUCH, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THERE ARE NO SPEAKERS. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE FOR ADOPTION OF THAT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 31 THROUGH 33 TOGETHER YES ITEM 31
THROUGH 33 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE. A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TODAY.
ANY SUPERVISOR MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE
TO GO TO COMMITTEE. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL DO I HAVE
THE NEW SYSTEM RIGHT? I DO.
CAN I EVER ITEM NUMBER 33 PLEASE?
>> OKAY. >> SUPERVISOR WONG LIKE TO ADD
MY NAME AS A CO-SPONSOR TO ITEM 30 ONE.
>> OKAY. >> I THINK THAT'S EVERYBODY.
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEMS 31 AND 32 ON ITEMS 31 AND 32.
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSI DORSI EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN EYE RANDLEMAN EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR ABSENT SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE TEN EYES
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEM THREE ITEM 33 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
DECLARE THE MONTH OF SEPTEMBER 2026 AS NATIONAL SERVICE DOG
MONTH IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL THANK YOU PRESIDENT MIDDLEMEN COLLEAGUES
TODAY I AM VERY PLEASED TO BE VOTING ON THIS RESOLUTION
RECOGNIZING SEPTEMBER 2026 AS NATIONAL SERVICE DOG MONTH HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. SINCE 1975 CANINE COMPANIONS
HAS PROVIDED EXPERTLY TRAINED DOGS SERVICE DOGS EXCUSE ME
FREE OF CHARGE TO ADULTS, CHILDREN AND VETERANS WITH
DISABILITIES AS WELL AS FACILITY DOGS TO HEALTH CARE,
EDUCATION AND CRIMINAL JUSTICE PROFESSIONALS LOCALLY.
THE SAN FRANCISCO SOUTH BAY CHAPTER CARRIES THIS MISSION
FORWARD RAISING AWARENESS, RECRUITING VOLUNTEERS
AND BUILDING COMMUNITY ACROSS SANTA CLARA.
SANTA CRUZ, SAN MATEO AND SAN FRANCISCO COUNTIES.
EARLIER TODAY MY OFFICE HOSTED CANINE COMPANIONS AND FOUR
FANTASTIC PUPPIES. AM I GOING TO GET THIS RIGHT?
CORNELIUS JOY AND I FORGOT THE OTHER TWO BUT THEY WERE REALLY
CUTE TOO FOR A MEET AND GREET BEFORE TODAY'S MEETING I'M
EXCITED TO VOTE ON THIS. I WANT TO THANK MY CO SPONSORS
SUPERVISORS CHAN CHEN MIDDLEMAN, MELGAR, WONG SAUTER,
DORSEY MAHMOOD AND FIELDER FOR THEIR SUPPORT AND I ESPECIALLY
WANT TO THANK THE CANINE COMPANIONS TEAMS WHO ARE HERE
TODAY. DAVE LASKER KATHY JAVA.
DAVE BLAIR. ELLEN TUCKER.
JANET CORSETTI. AUDREY CURRAN FROM CANINE
COMPANIONS AND OF COURSE THE WONDERFUL AND BEAUTIFUL DOGS.
I ENCOURAGE EVERYONE TO LEARN MORE ABOUT SERVICE DOGS AND THE
IMPACT THEY HAVE ON HELPING PEOPLE.
THESE DOGS OFFER MORE THAN ASSISTANCE.
THEY OFFER INDEPENDENCE CONNECTION AND ESPECIALLY
DIGNITY TO THE PEOPLE WHO NEED IT MOST CANINE COMPANIONS.
THANK YOU ALL SO MUCH AND TO YOUR VOLUNTEERS FOR YOUR
COMPASSION AND DEDICATION TO OUR COMMUNITY.
ALL RIGHT. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE AND CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY
IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS? NONE TO REPORT.
MR. PRESIDENT, CAN YOU PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM?
>> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE
FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR
THE LATE MISS VIVIAN AND HOPKINS.
MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US
TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY AND WE ARE ADJOURNED